(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-07T00:56:07.452586",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
グッドモーニングのじゃー！
Good morning, noja!
のじゃー！
Noja!
よいしょ。
Yoisho.
あいさつするのじゃ。
I'll do the greetings, noja.
あらあら、メラメラ、あちち、メラ！
Ara-ara, Melamela, achichi, mela!
ホロライブアソビまわりたい御利益担当のひけしサラマンダー、
The firefighter salamander in charge of blessings for Hololive Asobi Mawari-tai...
あちちメラなのじゃー！
Achichi Mela, noja~!
BGM二つになったのじゃ。
The background music doubled, noja.
おはよーのじゃー！
Good morning, noja!
グッドモーニング、 or
Good morning, or...
グッドイブニング、 or
Good evening, or...
ハローなののじゃ。
Hello, noja.
のじゃ。
Noja.
え？
Eh?
のじゃ！のじゃ！
Noja! Noja!
だ、大丈夫？
A-Are you okay?
き、聞こえる？聞こえるのじゃ？
C-Can you hear me? Can you hear me, noja?
のじゃー。
Noja~
You guys okay? オッケーのじゃ？
You guys okay? Okay, noja?
オンライン？
Online?
I'm back?
サンキューのじゃー！
Thank you, noja!
のじゃー。
Noja~
切れちゃったっぽい。
It seems like it cut out.
えっと、ちょっと待ってほしいのじゃ。
Um, please wait a moment, noja.
ちょっと待ってほしいのじゃ。
Please wait a moment, noja.
なんか設定が難しくて、
The settings are kind of difficult...
あんまりまだ分かってない。
and I still don't really understand them yet.
よいしょ。
Yoisho.
え、また切れた？What? What? のじゃ？
Eh, disconnected again? What? What? Noja?
今オッケー？今オッケー？
Is it okay now? Is it okay now?
ラグい？
Is it laggy?
BGM再び？のじゃーーー！
The BGM again? Nojaaa!
トラブル！メニー、メニートラブル！
Trouble! Many, many troubles!
ソーリー！ソーリーなのじゃ！
Sorry! Sorry, noja!
ど、どうしよう？ソーリーのじゃ。
W-What should I do? Sorry, noja.
のじゃー。
Noja~
オッケー？オッケー？オッケー？
Okay? Okay? Okay?
のじゃー！朝からごめんのじゃ！
Noja! Sorry so early in the morning, noja!
よいしょ、よいしょ、よいしょ。
Yoisho, yoisho, yoisho.
もう、朝なのに、
Jeez, even though it's morning...
モーニングなのに、
even though it's morning...
いっぱいトラブル。
so many troubles.
いっぱいトラブルで、あの、起きた。
With all these troubles, um, I woke up.
I wake up!
うん、逆にね。
Yeah, conversely.
逆に起きたのじゃ。おはようなのじゃー！
Conversely, I woke up, noja. Good morning, noja!
あのね、あのねあのね、
You know, you know, you know...
今日はのじゃイングリッシュだから、
Today is Noja English, so...
いっぱい寝た。
I slept a lot.
あの、8時間寝た。
Um, I slept for 8 hours.
I sleep!
えいとはわ、合ってる？ うん。
Eight hours, is that correct? Yeah.
早く寝たよ。昨日10時。22時に寝た。
I went to bed early. 10:00 last night. I went to bed at 22:00.
22時に寝ますのじゃ。
I went to bed at 22:00, noja.
今日、朝のために。それでね、6時...
To prepare for this morning. And then, at 6:00...
シックス、に起きた。
Six, I woke up.
うん。いっぱい寝ましたのじゃ。
Yeah. I got plenty of sleep, noja.
そっちはまだ夜？
Is it still night over there?
ユーガイズ ナイト？ ナイト？
You guys night? Night?
ジャパン イズ モーニング。午後6時？
Japan is morning. 6 PM?
シックス PM。
6 PM.
ファイブ AM。
5 AM.
オア、イブニング。そう、イブニングだ。
Or evening. Yes, evening.
イレブン PM。いっぱいの時間。メニータイム、メニータイム。ミッドナイト、深夜。
11 PM. A lot of time. Many times, many times. Midnight, late night.
そうそう。つづり、つづりとキョーコ？
Yeah, yeah. Tsuzuri, Tsuzuri and Kyoko?
あの、遊び回りたいメンバーの、つづり ＆ キョーコは、あの、ストリーミングなの。
Those two members of "Asobi Mawaritai", Tsuzuri & Kyoko, are streaming.
ずっとね、あの、配信... ヴァロラント？ ヴァロラント？ オーバーウォッチ？
They've been streaming... Valorant? Valorant? Overwatch?
ごめん、ゲームが、ちゃんと理解できてない。
Sorry, I don't quite understand the game well.
あの、FPS、FPSの、なんか耐久配信をしてた。
Um, FPS. They were doing an endurance stream of an FPS game.
そう、ロング、ロングストリームをね、してた。
Yeah, they were doing a long, long stream.
オーバーウォッチ、オーバーウォッチをね、してた。
Overwatch, they were playing Overwatch.
うん。
Yeah.
めちゃ頑張ってるのじゃ。すごいのじゃ。
They are working so hard, noja. That's amazing, noja.
ねえ。耐久なのじゃ。うん。
Right? It's an endurance stream, noja. Yeah.
「Crazy」 確かに、確かにめっちゃ長い。
"Crazy" Indeed, indeed it is super long.
うん、体力、体力すごいのじゃ。うん。
Yeah, their stamina, their stamina is amazing, noja. Yeah.
なんか気合い入れてたよ。うん。
They seemed really motivated. Yeah.
で、メラは、イングリッシュ...
And, Mela is doing English...
スタディ、ストリームをするんじゃが、あのね、あの...
study stream, but you see...
前回のデュオリンゴの配信で、あの、おぬしらめっちゃ簡単って思わなかった？
In my last Duolingo stream, didn't you guys think it was way too easy?
あの、I thought Duolingo was too easy、あの、前のストリーム。
Um, "I thought Duolingo was too easy" in the previous stream.
そう、で、思って、そう、I tried、あの...
Right, so I thought, yeah, I tried...
テスト、スキッピング。そう、飛び級？
the test skipping. Yeah, skipping?
飛び級しようと思って、I tried skipping ahead to Section 3.
I thought about skipping ahead. I tried skipping ahead to Section 3.
そう、Section 2をやってて、Too easyだったから、あの、スキップしようとしたの。そう。
Yeah, I was doing Section 2, and since it was too easy, I tried to skip it. Yeah.
But！ しかし、あの、I failed！ そう。
But! However, um, I failed! Yeah.
あは、あの、難しくて、It's hard for me. そう、難しかった、難しくて、あの...
Haha, um, it was difficult. "It's hard for me." Yeah, it was difficult. It was so hard that...
Section 3が、あの、だめ、だめだった。I can't skip. そう。
Section 3 was, um, a no-go. It was no good. I can't skip. Yeah.
Too difficult for me. そう、だめじゃった。
"Too difficult for me." Yeah, it was a no-go.
から、あの、またいつか挑戦する。
So, um, I'll try again sometime.
うん。またいつか挑戦する。から、ベーシックからやろうと思うのじゃ。
Yeah. I'll try again sometime. So I think I'll start from the basics, noja.
え、もう一回、おぬしらと一緒にやってみる？
Should we try doing it together again?
今日、朝やってだめだったやつ、もう一回おぬしらとやってみる？
The one I failed this morning, do you want to try it again with me?
ちょっとどんなの、見てみる？ 一旦。
Do you want to see what it's like? For now.
一旦見てみる？ おぬしら。
Do you guys want to see it for now?
You guys want to see test? 見たい？
"You guys want to see the test?" Do you want to see it?
じゃ、一回見せてあげる。一回見せてあげるのじゃ。うん。
Then, I'll show you once. I'll show you once, noja. Yeah.
えっと、じゃあ、お勉強のお部屋に行こうと思うから、あ...
Well, then, I'm going to head to the study room, so...
You guys already push like?
Have you guys already pushed like?
Already liked my video? グッドボタンを押してくれましたかのじゃ？
"Already liked my video?" Have you pressed the like button, noja?
Please subscribe to my channel, and push like, good button, to take off my mask, noja!
Please subscribe to my channel, and push like, the good button, to take off my mask, noja!
Thank you のじゃー！
Thank you, noja!
じゃ、行くのじゃ。よいしょ。
Well, let's go. There we go.
おはようのじゃー。
Good morning, noja!
うーん、よいしょ。
Mmh, there we go.
んで、ええと、I...
And, let's see, I...
どれだっけ？
Which one was it?
So, this is Section 2.
前回やったのがこれね。
What I did last time was this.
前回やったのがこれで、これがセクション2で...
What I did last time was this, and this is Section 2...
This is Section 2.
And I tried this.
セクション3、「I know some words in English」。
Section 3, "I know some words in English".
そう、ちょっとは単語知ってますよ、英語の。
Yes, "I know some words in English".
そう、ちょっとは英単語知ってますのところに、あのー、飛び級しようと思って。
Yeah, so I thought I'd skip ahead to the "I know some words" part.
そう、I tried this.
Right, so I tried this.
Actually, I think I know some words in English. 知ってると思う。
Actually, I think I know some words in English. I think I do.
そう。
Yeah.
自認ね。わしは知ってるつもりじゃから...
Self-acknowledgement. Since I think I know them...
これをやったんじゃけど。
I tried this.
オッケー。見せてあげる。
Okay. I'll show you.
このテストをクリアして「セクション3」まで飛び級しよう！
Clear this test to skip ahead to Section 3!
Pass this test to 飛び級チャレンジ Section 3.
Pass this test to challenge-skip to Section 3.
うん。
Yeah.
で、やろうとしたの。充電する。
So I was trying to do it. "To charge".
Charge.
あ、音聴こえる？主ら。
Ah, can you hear the sound, everyone?
Charge.
でかいかな？
Is it too loud?
Is it too big?
Charge.
どうじゃ？
How is it?
Sounds good?
うるさい？
Is it too loud?
いい感じかの？
Is it just right?
オッケー、オッケー。Too big? Okay.
Okay, okay. Too loud? Okay.
Charge.
オッケー？It's okay?
Okay? It's okay?
Charge.
いい感じか？Okay, good. Okay, okay, okay.
Is it just right? Okay, good. Okay, okay, okay.
じゃあ、これで。Charge。充電する。
So, with this... Charge. To charge.
待って、前回と問題違う！問題が違うのじゃ！
Wait, the questions are different from last time! The questions are different, noja!
オッケー。
Okay.
次へ。
Next.
Is this place safe?
Is this place safe? ここは、ここは安全ですか？
Is this place safe? Is this place safe?
安全ですか？え、今回簡単かも！前回よりも、あの、easy! easyかも！
Is it safe? Eh, it might be easy this time! Even more than last time, easy! Maybe it's easy!
前もっと簡単... 難しかった。
Last time was simpler... it was harder.
オッケー。
Okay.
忘れる。forget.
To forget. Forget.
forget.
うん、うん。え、なんか前回より簡単かも。え、運ゲーのじゃ、これ？
Yeah, yeah. Eh, somehow it might be easier than last time. Eh, is this a luck-based game?
Don't wear shoes inside.
Don't wear shoes inside. えっと、室内で...
Don't wear shoes inside. Let's see, "indoors"...
えーーー
Uhhh...
靴を履かないでください。
Please do not wear shoes.
室内で靴を履かないでください。オッケー。
Please do not wear shoes indoors. Okay.
え、運ゲー？ご利益担当なのじゃ。これ、もしかして、もしかしてこれ、あの...
Eh, a game of luck? I'm the one in charge of blessings. Maybe, just maybe, this...
配信、配信で運がいい、わしの、やつの、のじゃ？
My luck is good because of the stream, is that it, noja?
普段よりもの実力が、あれか？So, question changed.
My skills are better than usual? So, the questions changed.
変わっちゃったのじゃ。バフが、バフがのってるのじゃ！
They changed, noja. A buff! I've got a buff, noja!
橋。bridge.
Bridge. Bridge.
bridge.
オッケー。え、配信バフ可能性ありのじゃ。bridge。
Okay. Eh, there's a possibility of a stream buff, noja. Bridge.
Don't drive on that road.
Don't drive on that road. えっと、その道で運転しないで。
Don't drive on that road. Let's see, "Don't drive on that road".
よいしょ。え、easy!
There we go. Eh, easy!
待って！楽しむ。have fun.
Wait! To enjoy. Have fun.
have fun.
え、Duolingo is watching my stream?
Eh, Duolingo is watching my stream?
Duolingo見てる？
Is Duolingo watching?
Hurry, you're late. 遅いからハヨセイ！
Hurry, you're late. You're slow, so hurry up!
オッケー。え、待って。まだライフが3ある。
Okay. Eh, wait. I still have three lives.
ライフ0になったのに。まじのじゃ？
Even though my lives went down to zero. Really, noja?
のじゃ！え、easy, easy. オッケー。
Noja! Eh, easy, easy. Okay.
Be なんちゃら, this area is dangerous at night. Be careful, noja. Careful.
Be something, this area is dangerous at night. Be careful, noja. Careful.
Careful. え、easyのじゃ、easyのじゃ。
Careful. Eh, it's easy, noja, it's easy!
いくら使っていますか？
How much are you spending?
えー、How much are you spending?
Let's see, "How much are you spending"?
じゃない？のじゃ。え、easy, easy. Too easyのじゃ。Why? なんで？なんでのじゃ？
Isn't it? Noja. Eh, easy, easy. Too easy, noja. Why? Why? Why, noja?
もっと難しかったのじゃ。
It was much harder before, noja.
Good.
忘れたのじゃ
I forgot!
どんな問題じゃったかも忘れてないけど、これむず、むずって思ったのじゃ
I haven't forgotten what kind of question it was, but I thought it was hard, so hard!
I always spend too much... なんちゃら at the store. Money のじゃ！ え？
"I always spend too much..." something "...at the store." It's "money"! Huh?
イージーすぎないのじゃ？
Isn't this too easy?
Why? なんで？
Why? Why?
のじゃあ！
Noja!
Too easyですのじゃー！
It's too easy!
なんで？ こんなのアリ？
Why? Is this allowed?
こんなのアリ？
Is this allowed?
そのことは心配しないで。Don't worry about...
For "don't worry about that," "Don't worry about..."
Don't worry about that.
えええ！？
What!?
待って、イージー、イージー！ Why!?
Wait, this is so easy! Why!?
え、もしかしてわし...
Wait, could it be that I...
セクション4、4チャレンジしてたのじゃ？
Was challenging Section 4? Really?
[Audio] Please, come inside.
Please...
come inside.
よいしょ。
There we go.
え、Too easyのじゃ！ Too easyのじゃ！
Eh, it's too easy! It's too easy!
一緒に橋を渡ろう。
Let's cross the bridge together.
えーー、あ、これ分かんない。
Uh... oh, I don't know this one.
えーー、Let's...
Uh... Let's...
Let's...
えーー、渡るって何じゃろ？
Uh... what is "cross"?
まあいいや。
Well, whatever.
Let's なんちゃら bridge, bridge...
Let's [something] bridge, bridge...
togetherだと思うんだよ。together.
I think "together" goes there. Together.
Let's... 渡るって何じゃろ？
Let's... what is "to cross"?
Let's pass! passとか。
Let's pass! Or maybe "pass"?
ちょ、一旦これで。のじゃ！
Wait, let's try this first. Noja!
Cross the street!?
Bridgeじゃないのじゃ？ Cross, Cross...
It's not "bridge"? Cross, cross...
あ、道！
Ah, street!
橋だと思った！
I thought it was "bridge"!
橋じゃない！
It's not bridge!
道なのじゃーー！
It's street!
I thought bridge. 日本語、ジャパニーズ間違えたのじゃ。
I thought "bridge." I got the Japanese wrong!
My Japanese is bad. のじゃ。
My Japanese is bad... Noja.
Cross the street together. のじゃ。
“Cross the street together,” I see.
私たちはプールに泳ぎに行きます。
We are going swimming at the pool.
We...
わしこういうの苦手。英訳超苦手、英訳超苦手。
I'm bad at these. I'm so bad at translating to English.
We... uh...
We are going...
to swimming... swimming.
のじゃ！
Noja!
「プールに」がない！
There's no "at the pool"!
We are going, going swimming at the pool.
なんで to ないの？ なんで to ないのじゃ？
Why is there no "to"? Why is there no "to"?
Why? Why no to? Why no to?
ingが重複？ ing, to ingはだめ？
Are the "ing"s duplicating? Is "to [ing]" not allowed?
Why? Why? Not bad?
We are going swimming at the pool.
To the pool, or going swimming...
To the pool...
不定詞？ to 不定詞？ わ、分かんない言葉来た！ 不定詞来た、不定詞！
Infinitive? "To" infinitive? Oh, a word I don't know showed up! Infinitive!
We are going to swim.
goingで、ingを使うなら、to swim?
If we use "going" with "ing," then is it "to swim"?
toがあるならswim？
If there's "to," then it's "swim"?
toのあとにingがつかない？ おーー。
So you don't put "ing" after "to"? Oh.
Going to swim, going swimming at the place.
ふーーん。不定詞ってなんじゃ？
Hmm... what is an infinitive?
To swim or swimming, not to swimming.
to... toはだめ？
So "to... to" is a no-no?
be going toで未来形？
Is "be going to" the future tense?
be... beがareじゃろ？
“be”... “be” is “are,” right?
ing, going...
あ、toのあとswimmingにするのはダメなのか。
Ah, so you can't put "swimming" after "to".
はーー、はーー、はーー。
Ah, I see, I see.
be going to 動詞。be going to 動詞なのじゃ。
“be going to” verb. It's “be going to verb”!
going... でも、toが模範解答にないからダメなのじゃ？
going... But "to" isn't in the correct answer, so it's not allowed?
To swim, what you will do.
Swimming, what you are doing.
あーー、じゃあ...
Ah, then...
じゃあ、to swimでもいいや。
Then "to swim" is fine too.
swimming what you're doing. でも「泳ぎ」「泳ぎ」...
“swimming is what you're doing,” but “oyogi”...
泳いでる状態になる？
Does it mean being in the state of swimming?
Go to swimならOK？
Is "go to swim" okay?
to swimなら大丈夫。
If it's "to swim", it's fine.
We are going to swim...
「at the pool」でもOK？
..."at the pool" is also okay?
だったのか。
So that was it.
「go swimming」が「泳ぎに行く」
"Go swimming" is "going to swim".
「go to swim」が「泳ぐために行く」、あ、
"Go to swim" is "going in order to swim". Oh,
意味が変わっちゃうのじゃ。細かいニュアンスが変わっちゃうっぽい。
The meaning changes! It seems like the subtle nuance changes.
どっちもOKだけど、
Both are okay, but...
なんか、より良いニュアンスにするには、
to get a better nuance,
goen... ん？ 「go swim」？
go... swim?
になるっぽい。
it seems like it becomes that.
「go V-ing」が自然な表現。OK。
"Go V-ing" is the natural expression. Okay.
じゃあこれは不自然な表現なのじゃ？ 「going to swim」？
Then is this an unnatural expression? "going to swim"?
うーん。
Hmm.
go shopping。
Go shopping.
うーん。
Hmm.
OK、じゃあ、なんか「〜しに行きます」の場合は、
Okay, then, in the case of "going to do something",
うーん。
Hmm.
でも正解は「going swimming」じゃからな。
But the correct answer is "going swimming".
え、ingが2回来るの不思議な感じするのじゃ。
Eh, it feels weird having "ing" twice.
不思議な感じする。
It feels weird.
ちょっとこれは、あの、経験でなんとかするしかないのじゃ。OK。
I'll just have to deal with this through experience. Okay.
驚異の集中力！次へ。
Amazing focus! Next.
え、でも、パス、パスかも！パス！
Eh, but, pass? Maybe a pass! Pass!
パスしたかも！パスしたかも！
I might have passed! I might have passed!
OKだったかも、のじゃ！
I might have been okay!
ちょ、ちょ、なんか、いっぱいある。
Wa- wait, there's a lot of things popping up.
ロックされた？アンロックのじゃ？
Locked? Unlocked?
アンロックのじゃ？
Unlocked?
ちょっといっぱい出てくる。
A lot of things are popping up.
後で。
Later.
ん？セクション3にチャレンジ権がある！
Hm? There's a challenge right for Section 3!
見て、ユーガイズ見て！アンロックのじゃ！
Look, you guys, look! Unlocked!
セクション3行ける！
I can go to Section 3!
やったー！
Yay!
やったのじゃ！なんか配信前の朝試した時は、
I did it! When I tried it this morning before the stream,
あの、ライフ0、最後の和訳のところで0じゃったんじゃが、
I had 0 lives, at the very last translation part, I had 0,
合格したのじゃー！
but I passed!
やったのじゃー！
I did it!
「最初のingは未来を示して、後のingは動名詞」出た、動名詞！
"The first -ing indicates the future, and the second -ing is a gerund." There it is, gerund!
あの、わしが授業で聞いても全く分からなかったやつ！
The thing that I didn't understand at all even when I heard it in class!
何？あの、ジャパニーズ...
What? The Japanese...
ジャパニーズおぬしらは、動名詞とか理解してるのじゃ？
Do you Japanese understand gerunds and stuff?
授業で理解できたタイプ？
Are you the type who could understand them in class?
わしは、
For me...
分からなかった。
I didn't understand.
わしは動名詞とかそういうの分からなかったのじゃ。
I didn't understand gerunds and stuff like that.
I can't understand 動名詞のじゃ。
I can't understand gerunds.
ちょっと待っててね。
Wait a moment, okay?
よいしょ。おじゃ。うん。
Yoisho. Oja. Un.
覚えるぞ。覚えるのじゃ。
I'll learn it. I'll learn it.
これからね、学ぶのじゃ。
From now on, I will learn.
わしと一緒に覚えるのじゃ、雰囲気じゃなくてね、
Learn it together with me, not just by the vibe,
確実に覚えるのじゃ。
but let's learn it definitely.
OK、じゃあ、セクション3「運動について話す」！
Okay, then, Section 3 "Talk about sports"!
運動ってなんじゃ？スポーツ？
What is "exercise"? Sports?
「Talk about sports」のじゃ。
"Talk about sports".
行くのじゃ。
Let's go.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Catch the ball.
音量OK？ちっちゃい？
Is the volume okay? Is it low?
「Catch...」「キャッチ」
"Catch..." "Catch"
「Catch the ball」、ボールを...
"Catch the ball." The ball...
キャッチして。
...catch.
OK、のじゃ。
Okay.
Wow, you read fast!
わあ、
Wow,
あなたは、
you...
読むのが早いよ。
...read fast.
うん、OK、のじゃ。
Yeah, okay.
That player always catches the ball.
catches。That player always catches the ball.
catches. That player always catches the ball.
そのプレイヤーは
That player...
いつもボールをキャッチする。
...always catches the ball.
空振らない？
They don't miss?
空振らないのじゃ。この辺はイージーのじゃ。
They don't miss. Around here it's easy.
I understand, I... 何？「理解できる」 - I can understand this。
I understand, I... what? "I can understand" - "I can understand this".
分かる。分かるけど、テスト難しかった。
I get it. I get it, but the test was hard.
えっと、Why do you always...
Um, "Why do you always..."
Why do you always walk fast?
Fast。
Fast.
なんでいつも早く歩くの？
Why do you always walk fast?
もっとゆっくり歩いてほしいのじゃ。
I want you to walk more slowly.
「Writing sentences is the hardest part.」 Yes!
"Writing sentences is the hardest part." Yes!
そう、そう。I... I'm not good at... あの、和訳...
Yes, yes. I... I'm not good at... um, translating...
ジャパニーズに、イングリッシュとジャパニーズ？ん？ノー。
Japanese... English to Japanese? Huh? No.
ジャパニーズ・トゥ・イングリッシュができない。
Japanese to English doesn't work.
そう、それができないのじゃ。
Yes, I can't do that.
次。空欄を埋めてください。I run fast. 早く走れます。
Next. "Fill in the blank." "I run fast." I can run fast.
She can run fast. 彼女も早く走れます。トム。
"She can run fast." She can also run fast. Tom.
トム、キャン、サーフ？
Tom... can... surf?
なんか一人だけ違う。
Somehow, only one person is different.
トムはドリブルが上手い！
Tom is good at dribbling!
いい感じ！のじゃ。のじゃ。
Nice! Noja. Noja.
なんで走りの話してるのにトムだけ、トムだけ、トムだけサーフの話？
Why is it only Tom talking about surfing when we're talking about running?
Why? Why Tom surf? Why surf?
何、のじゃ？
What, noja?
次。
Next.
トム来た。Yes, I can surf well. Oh...
Here comes Tom. "Yes, I can surf well." Oh...
ん？
Hmm?
fast too.
これ何？待って、これ分かんない。
What is this? Wait, I don't get this.
Yes, I can surf well. 私は、あの、サーフィンがめっちゃ上手くできますよ、Oh...
"Yes, I can surf well." I, like, can surf really well, oh...
Heじゃないよね。can fast too? run fast too?
It's not "He", right? "can fast too?" "run fast too?"
早く走れやってこと？
Does it mean "run fast too"?
あ。
Ah.
He can run fast too. あ、一個じゃないのか！
"He can run fast too." Oh, it's not just one!
Only oneじゃと思ってた。なるほど。
I thought it was only one. I see.
Yes, I can surf well. Oh, he can run fast too.
サーフィンもできるし、早く走ることもできますよってことか。オッケー、オッケー。
He can surf, and he can run fast too, is what it means? Okay, okay.
I thought、一個、一個だと思ってた。Only oneじゃと思ってた、選択するのは。三つね、オッケー、オッケー。
I thought... I thought it was just one to select. Three, okay, okay.
Got it. He can run very fast.
めっちゃ早く走れる。足が早い、オッケー。
He can run really fast. He's fast on his feet, okay.
Junior can... run fast.
さすがに「走る」じゃない？
It's gotta be "run", right?
ジュニアは早く走れる。足早が多いのじゃ。
Junior can run fast. There are many fast runners.
Many, many fast run people. 人間。Human.
Many, many fast run people. Humans.
Mela can run very fast?
メラは...遅いかな？メラは...メラはちょっと遅い。
Mela... is slow, maybe? Mela... Mela is a bit slow.
サラマンダーよりずっと早いって、ちょっと切ないやつって、わし知っているのじゃ。のじゃ。
I know that "way faster than a salamander" is a bit of a sad one. Noja.
Yes, Anna can run very fast.
アンナはめっちゃ早く走れる。Yes, Ben can swim well.
Anna can run really fast. "Yes, Ben can swim well."
ベンは泳ぐのが上手い。
Ben is good at swimming.
何、この会話？何、この会話？早く走れる。
What is this conversation? What is this conversation? He can run fast.
泳ぎも上手いぜ、のじゃ？What is this, noja? うーん、オッケー。
He's also good at swimming, noja? What is this, noja? Hmm, okay.
I can surf. サーフィンもできるのじゃ。サーフィンしたことないのじゃ。
"I can surf." I can surf too. But I've never surfed before.
Yes, I can swim. はい、泳げます。泳げます！
"Yes, I can swim." Yes, I can swim. I can swim!
パターンだから会話ではない。あ、なるほど、のじゃ。パターンのじゃ。会話じゃないのじゃ。
It's a pattern, so it's not a conversation. Ah, I see. It's a pattern. It's not a conversation.
My mom can swim. 私の母は泳げる。
"My mom can swim." My mother can swim.
My momは、どうかな？泳げるかの？My mom can swim? 知らないのじゃ。
How about my mom? Can she swim? "My mom can swim?" I don't know.
メラは、あの、I'm not good at...と思った。
I thought Mela, like, is not good at...
Swimming, because my 髪の毛からさ、my hairからさ、burningじゃからさ、見て、炎。
...swimming, because from my hair, like, my hair is burning. Look, fire.
炎あるのじゃ。Fire あるから。あの、犬かきならできるのじゃ。
There's fire. Because there's fire. I can do the doggy paddle, though.
犬かきってこれ何じゃ？調べよう。犬かき、犬かき。
What is doggy paddle? Let's look it up. Doggy paddle, doggy paddle.
うん、I can do the... doggy paddle. doggy paddle. うん。
Yeah, "I can do the... doggy paddle." Doggy paddle. Yeah.
犬かきで泳げる、I can swim doggy paddle swimming.
I can swim with doggy paddle. I can swim doggy paddle swimming.
できるのじゃ。うん。シャワーの時は火消すのじゃ。
I can do it. Yeah. When taking a shower, I turn off the fire.
のじゃ。うん。でもなんか、あの...
Noja. Yeah. But somehow, like...
クロールとか、普通の泳ぎは苦手
I'm not good at crawl or other normal swimming strokes.
平泳ぎとかそういうのはできないのじゃ、うん
Like, I can't do the breaststroke, yeah.
ドッグのやつのみできるのじゃ
I can only do the dog paddle.
うん、のじゃ
Yeah, noja.
お風呂入っているのじゃ
I take baths!
お風呂入る時は火消すのじゃ
When I take a bath, I turn off the fire.
あの、わしのね、髪の毛の火とね、どうなっているか知りたい人はね
Um, if you want to know what happens to the fire in my hair...
昨日投稿した自己紹介動画を見るとね、解明される
If you watch the self-introduction video I posted yesterday, it will explain it.
気がしますのじゃ、ぜひ見てほしいのじゃ
At least, I think so. Please check it out.
He never drives fast.
He never drives fast
え、彼は
"He" is "Kare wa"...
「Never」だから、彼は
Since it's "never"...
まったく…決してかな？
"Kesshite" (never) or "mattaku" (not at all)?
「決して」「早く」「運転しない」
"never" "drives" "fast."
「Never」、「Never」って何じゃ？
What is "never" again?
まったく？まったくか？
Is it "mattaku" (not at all)?
「まったく」「早く」「運転しない」
"Not at all" "drives" "fast."
「決して」じゃった、別の表現で、あ、なんでもいいんじゃ
Ah, it accepted "kesshite" (never) as an alternative. So either is fine.
なんでもいいんじゃな、ふむふむ
Either is fine, I see.
Yes, yesterday's self-introduce video had more about the fire in my hair.
So, watch, watch that.
So, I said that. うん
"So, I said that." Yes.
どっちもOK、He never drives fast.
Both are okay. "He never drives fast."
They can run fast!
なんか、走る速さが
Like, how fast someone runs...
あの、序列に繋がってそうな場所
is the kind of place that sets the pecking order.
早く走れたらモテる的な、小学生価値観のじゃ
Running fast makes you popular. Standard elementary school mindset.
いい調子、OK
Doing great, okay.
Are there English translations on that video?
あ、Not yet!
Ah, not yet!
え、聞いてみよう
Let's see.
いつか付けられるように
So that I can add them someday,
I try to make English translation.
Wait for it.
待ってほしいのじゃ
Please wait for it.
え、メモしとこう、忘れないように
Oh, let me take a note so I don't forget.
待って
Wait.
つけたい、ちょっと待ってね
I want to add them. Hold on.
手元にメモがあるから書くのじゃ
I have a notepad here, so I'll write it down.
えっと、自己紹介
Let's see, "self-introduction"...
イングリッシュ
"English"...
トランスレーション、OK
"translation", okay.
OK. I try it, noja.
Okay. "I... try... it, noja."
Wait, noja.
OK
Okay.
え、彼はとても早く走れる
Uh, "He can run very fast."
He...
He
can
run
very
fast
うん
Yep.
ボールをキャッチできるよね？
"You can catch a ball, right?"
あ、Can you...
Ah, "Can you..."
can
you
catch
あ、a ball...
Ah, "a ball..."
a
ball
あ、「right」もいるの？なくてもいいらしい
Oh, do we need "right"? Apparently, it works without it.
「よね？」
"Right?"
I... I remember. 覚えてるよ、覚えてるのじゃ
"I... I remember." I remember, I remember!
Achichi Mela is cute, right?
覚えてる。I... I know, I know.
I remember. "I... I know, I know."
知ってるのじゃ
I know.
I know!
知ってるのじゃ。Remember right? Yes, yes, yes
I know! "Remember right?" Yes, yes, yes.
やったやったやったやったやった、のじゃ
Yay, yay, yay, yay, yay, noja!
わかるのじゃ
I get it.
Yes
OK, you guys
Okay, you guys.
Achichi Mela is so cute, right?
Right?
うん、うん、うん、のじゃ
Mmhmm, mmhmm, noja.
Yes, Achichi Mela is pretty cute, right?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. OK, I...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. Okay, I...
覚えてる
...remember.
覚えてるのじゃ。Remember, remember noja.
I remember. "Remember, remember noja."
のじゃ
Noja.
え、トムはボールをとても上手にキャッチできる
Uh, "Tom can catch a ball very well."
Tom...
Tom
can
catch
あ、a ball...
Ah, "a ball..."
a
ball
very
well
のじゃ
Noja!
うん、yes, yes, yes
Yeah, yes, yes, yes.
やった、クリアしたのじゃ！OK!
Yay, I cleared it, noja! OK!
のじゃ
Noja.
運動について話す、スポーツについて話す
Talking about exercise, talking about sports.
Kick the ball!
ボールを
"Ball"...
蹴る
"kick."
けれ
"Kere" (Kick).
けれ？
"Kere"?
「ボールを」「けれ」
"Kick the ball."
のじゃー！
Noja!
Don't kick my chair!
やなやつ、椅子蹴るのダメ
What a mean person, don't kick my chair.
椅子…
Chair...
蹴るのダメ。
No kicking.
You guys...
...don't kick chair.
...don't kick the chair.
あの、シアターとかで...
Like, in theatres...
映画館とかでさ...
...or movie theaters...
チェ、チェアをさ、蹴る人がいる。
...there are people who kick the chairs.
やだ。
I hate that.
やだ！
I hate it!
蹴らないで！Don't kick my chair!
Don't kick it! Don't kick my chair!
やだのじゃ！
I hate it, noja!
うーん...
Yeah...
そう、that's rude. そう、のっとのっと！
Yeah, that's rude. Right, don't, don't!
だめ、やらないやつ。
No, don't do that.
だから一番後ろに座る？
Is that why you sit in the very back?
対策のじゃ、うーん。
That's a good solution, mhm.
"I will push your chair instead." 押さなくていいよ。Don't push.
"I will push your chair instead." No need to push. Don't push.
押さなくてもいいのじゃ。オッケー？
You don't need to push either, noja. Okay?
Throw the ball.
ボールを、投げて。
冒頭に動詞がきて、びっくりとかがつくと、命令形って聞いたのじゃ。
I heard that when a verb comes first, followed by an exclamation mark, it's an imperative.
命令形。
An imperative sentence.
命令。
Imperative.
うーん。
Yep.
Emma swims every day. エマは毎日泳ぎます。
Emma swims every day. Emma swims every day.
Max can't swim. マックスは泳げません。
Max can't swim. Max can't swim.
He can't... what? play or plays?
He can't play in the water.
なんでだろう？確かに、どういう時に「s」つくだ？
I wonder why. When exactly do we add "s"?
なんか「He plays」とか...
Like, "He plays"...
なんか「can't」がなかったら、「can't」がなかったら...
If there wasn't a "can't", if there was no "can't"...
...I think「s」だと思うんじゃが...
...I think it would have an "s"...
ひっかけ？
Is it a trick question?
「can't」の後に「After can't no S」あ、
"After can't, no S." Ah,
I know! 知ってた！knew, I knew, I knew! 知ってたのじゃ、知ってたのじゃ！
I know! I knew it! Knew, I knew, I knew! I knew it, I knew it, noja!
三単現、can'tがある、あ！
Third-person singular... because there's a "can't"! Ah!
なるほど。
I see.
canの後は、noなんだ。
So after "can", it's always the base form.
助動詞の後は、原型。助動詞ってなんじゃ？
After an auxiliary verb, it's the base form. What's an auxiliary verb?
What is 助動詞？
What is an auxiliary verb?
助動詞って何？
What are auxiliary verbs?
助動詞ってどれ？
Which one is the auxiliary verb?
can't？can't is 助動詞？
Can't? Is "can't" an auxiliary verb?
大惨事は違うのじゃ！
That's not a disaster, noja!
ん？canは助動詞。
Huh? "Can" is an auxiliary verb.
あ、canが助動詞。
Ah, "can" is the auxiliary verb.
動詞の原型、にょ？
Base form of the verb? Nyo?
canとかwillってのが助動詞。canとwill。
Things like "can" or "will" are auxiliary verbs. "Can" and "will".
へえ。のじゃ。
I see, noja.
うーん。
Mhm.
Yes, can is auxiliary verb.
Yes, "can" is an auxiliary verb.
Auxiliary verb. 助動詞。
Auxiliary verb. Auxiliary verb.
うーん。
Mhm.
オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay.
うーーん。
Mmm...
いじゃ、あの、無意識のうちに、文法を理解していた、わし。
So, I actually understood grammar unconsciously.
なぜか選べた。「play」がちゃんと選べた、わし。
I was able to choose it for some reason. I correctly chose "play".
麻雀知ってる口なのじゃ？ちょっとだけわかる。
Do you know how to play Mahjong? I know a little bit.
ちょっと。
Just a little.
アレろ、わかるのじゃ。
I know rules like that.
She can throw and catch very well.
めっちゃ上手に投げたり、取ったりできるのじゃ。
She can throw and catch really well, noja.
She can't throw a ball.
彼女はボールを投げられないのじゃ。
She cannot throw a ball, noja.
She throws the ball far.
遠くにボールを投げます。
She can throw the ball far.
遠くにボールを、ん？違うな、canじゃない。
She can throw... Wait, no, there's no "can".
She throws the ball far. 彼女は遠くにボールを投げます。
She throws the ball far. She throws the ball far.
彼女は遠くにボールを投げられます。
She can throw the ball far.
Lisa can...
...throw the ball far. 見て、can、あの
...throw the ball far. Look, after "can",
助動詞の後は「s」つかない。
an auxiliary verb, we don't add "s".
We don't add "s" after an auxiliary verb.
うーん。
Mhm.
This is showing you when to use... when to use the 's'.
確かに、確かに。
Indeed, indeed.
She throws, throws, the ball far. canがないね。
"She throws, throws, the ball far." There is no "can".
She can throw, sない、no s。
"She can throw." There's no "s". No "s".
Lisa can throw the ball far.
canだから、sないのじゃ。
Since it's "can", there's no "s", noja.
オッケー。
Okay.
遠い、far。
Far, far.
遠いのじゃ。
It means "far", noja.
Ben, can you kick this ball?
このボールを蹴れますか？
Can you kick this ball?
I can't swim.
泳げませんのじゃ。
I can't swim, noja.
Is Tom good at football?
Yes, he makes really great cakes, not cakes...
No, he can't throw a ball very far.
フットボールって投げるの？
Do you throw the ball in football?
Do they throw the ball in football?
フットボールって投げるの？
フットボールってさ...
Football...
Football.
ハンド？
Hands?
あ、アメリカンフットボール！アメリカンフットボール！オーケー、オーケー、オーケー、分かった、分かった、分かった。
Ah, American football! American football! Okay, okay, okay, I got it, I understand, I understand.
のじゃ。
Noja.
アメリカンフットボールね、オーケー、オーケー、オーケー、オーケー。
American football, right? Okay, okay, okay, okay.
Your...
Your なんちゃら can kick the ball very far, right? Your...
"Your" something "can kick the ball very far, right? Your..."
ああ、neighborかな？
Oh, "neighbor", maybe?
ポテトじゃないし、シャンプーでもないし。
It's not potato, nor shampoo.
あなたの隣人は、
"Your neighbor..."
遠くにボールを蹴れます。
"...can kick the ball far."
のじゃ。
Noja.
オーケー。
Okay.
Why are you good at soccer?
Why are you good at soccer? なんでサッカーそんな上手なの？
Why are you good at soccer? Why are you so good at soccer?
I don't have my wallet right now. What?
I can kick a ball very far.
これ答え合ってないのじゃ。Why are you good at soccer?
This answer doesn't match. Why are you good at soccer?
なんでそんな、あ、でもこれ、合ってるか。なんで上手なん？
Why so... Oh, but does this make sense? Why are you good?
ボールを遠くに蹴れるからなのじゃ。
"Because I can kick a ball very far," noja.
まあ、まあ、まあか。まあか。
Well, well, I guess so. I guess.
まあ、まあ、まあ、まあオーケーか。
Well, well, well, well, I guess it's okay.
うん。
Yeah.
These questions are too weird. Yes, I think so too. I think so too.
I can't run very far.
えーっと、
Let's see...
遠くまで、あまり... I can't run very far.
Far away, not very... I can't run very far.
あまり遠くまで走れない。
I cannot run very far.
のじゃ。
Noja.
いい調子？オーケー。
Good progress? Okay.
Why are you so cute, noja?
なんでじゃと思う？Because you guys tell me cute many, a lot.
Why do you think? Because you guys tell me cute many, a lot.
You guys tell me cute, so...
I am cute, noja.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Yes, because you said cute to me.
オーケー。
Okay.
うん。
Yeah.
のじゃ。
Noja.
えーっと、I...
Let's see, I...
I
can...
can
kick...
kick the...
ball...
ball
very かな？
very, maybe?
too、tooは違う。
too, too is wrong.
too farって言わなくない？
Don't they say "too far"?
far
too farって聞かない。なんでだ？
I've never heard "too far". Why?
なんでじゃ？
Why is that?
too far聞いたことない。
I've never heard "too far".
のじゃ。
Noja.
聞いたことない。なんでじゃろ？
I've never heard it. Why is that?
very farは言うけど、
I've heard "very far", but...
too far聞いたことないよ。
I've never heard "too far".
なんでじゃ？
Why is that?
なんか、聞いたことあるかないかで英語を判断している。
I judge English by whether I've heard it before or not.
うーん。
Hmm.
tooだとちょっとネガティブなニュアンス。
"too" has a slightly negative nuance.
遠すぎる。too farは、
Too far. "too far" is...
遅すぎる？
too slow?
うーん、遠すぎる。
Hmm, too far.
tooはすぎる、うーん。
"too" means "too much", hmm.
遠すぎ。
Too far.
すぎる。うーん、じゃ、遠くへじゃないのか。
"too much". Hmm, so it doesn't mean "far away"?
うーん。
Hmm.
too far、遠すぎる。
"too far" means "too far".
ほー、限界を超えている。
Oh, it exceeds the limit.
のじゃ。
Noja.
良くない、too far is not good. オーケー、オーケー、オーケー、オーケー。
Not good. "too far is not good." Okay, okay, okay, okay.
ニュアンスが変わっちゃうのじゃ。
The nuance changes, noja.
なるほどなのじゃ。
I see, noja.
うーん。
Hmm.
コメントは、あ、でもバット！あの問題を解く時、
The comments are... Ah, but but! When solving questions,
when I...
question... When I answer question,
question... When I answer questions,
I don't watch comments.
So, I, after I answer the question, I watch comment.
So, I, after I answer the question, I watch comments.
チャット。
Chat.
うん、after I answer。だから、あの、you guysは、
Yeah, after I answer. So, you guys...
えーっと、オーケー。書いていいよ。
...um, okay. You can write.
書いていいのじゃ。
You can write, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
スポイラー、うん。
Spoilers, yeah.
オーケーなのじゃ。
It's okay, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
Only I answer,
Only when I answer...
うん。
Yeah.
I don't watch chat when I answer question.
I don't watch chat when I answer questions.
オーケー。
Okay.
Okay, no cheating, okay?
うーん。
Hmm.
おけのじゃ。
Okay, noja.
から You guys あの...
So, you guys...
... can write your answer in chat, um.
書いていいよ。
You can write it down.
Because I don't watch, um.
Because I won't look.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Okay.
次。
Next.
サッカーボールが蹴れない！
I can't kick a soccer ball!
I can't kick...
ボールがない。
There's no ball.
あ、ボールあった。
Ah, there's a ball.
I can't kick a soccer ball.
うん。
Yep.
え、彼女はボールが投げられない。
Uh, she can't throw a ball.
She can't throw a ball.
Okay.
全問正解！Great のじゃ！
All correct! Great noja!
Perfect のじゃ！Okay.
Perfect noja! Okay.
Okay.
運動について話す。
Talking about exercise.
えー、もわ。
Uh, more.
Okay.
Football? This Duolingo is so wrong.
Not soccer? Football? Football?
さっきの問題が the ball だったのがもやる。何で何で何で？
It's annoying that the last question had "the ball." Why, why, why?
the ball じゃなくて a ball なのじゃ？
Isn't it supposed to be "a ball" instead of "the ball," noja?
わし、a と the の違いがあまり分かってないのじゃ。
I don't really know the difference between "a" and "the," noja.
It's soccer. Football yes.
これ派閥か？
Is this a faction war?
Okay.
Soccer is American... あ、
Soccer is American... Ah,
Okay. なんか
Okay. It seems...
コメント欄でも荒れてる。チャット欄でも。これアメリカ英語？
...there's a debate in the comments and the chat. Is this American English?
It's American English.
なるほどね。派閥があるのね。
I see. So there are factions.
あんま、あんま触れなきゃよかった？あんま触れない方がいいやつなのじゃ？
Should I not have mentioned it? Is it better not to touch upon it, noja?
うー。Okay, okay, okay.
Ooh. Okay, okay, okay.
なんかあるのね。どっちかみたいなのがあって、
So there's some kind of rivalry going on...
Duolingo は、あの、サッカーのやつ？
...and Duolingo uses the soccer one?
"Japan calls it soccer, too." Yes, Japan も、
"Japan calls it soccer, too." Yes, Japan too,
Japan でものじゃ。
even in Japan, noja.
あ、ひ、ひ、ひ、火の、火の用心じゃ！火の用心じゃ！
Ah, f- f- fire... fire safety! Fire safety!
のじゃのじゃのじゃ！無知は、無知は争いを生みますのじゃ！
Noja, noja, noja! Ignorance, ignorance breeds conflict, noja!
のじゃー！
Noja!
なるほど。あの、きのこたけのこ的な感じのじゃ。
I see. It's like the Mushroom vs. Bamboo Shoot war, noja.
のじゃのじゃのじゃ。
Noja, noja, noja.
いや、やはりね、あの、炎上はいかにして起こるかっていう話なんだが、
Well, as expected, when it comes to how fires break out...
無知なのじゃ。ズバリ。
...it's ignorance. Pure and simple.
悪意のない炎上というのは無知によって起こりますのじゃ。
Fires without malicious intent are caused by ignorance, noja.
うん。知らないということは罪ですのじゃ。
Yeah. Not knowing is a sin, noja.
あの、知らないことは実は罪ではそんなないんじゃが、
Well, not knowing actually isn't much of a sin itself...
表に出て、配信をしたり発信活動をする人間が
...but for someone who goes out in public, streams, or does broadcast activities...
知らないというのは、なかなかにギルティですのじゃ。
...to not know is quite guilty, noja.
火の用心じゃー！
Fire safety!
Okay. Okay, noja. Okay, okay, okay.
"Be careful for fire." Okay. Okay, okay, okay.
Be careful, be careful, noja!
のじゃ。Fire safety first, noja.
Noja. Fire safety first, noja.
Okay. のじゃ。
Okay. Noja.
よし、じゃあ、重り。重り選ぶのじゃ。Next! Next のじゃ！
Alright, then, weights. Let's choose weights, noja. Next! Next, noja!
ちなみにメラちゃんたけのこ派ですか？
"By the way, Mela-chan, are you on Team Bamboo Shoot?"
燃やそうとするな！燃やそうとするな！わしの配信を、わしの配信を燃やそうとするな！のじゃ！
Don't try to start a fire! Don't try to set my stream, my stream on fire! Noja!
weight. weight のじゃ。
weight. Weight, noja.
うん。
Yep.
あの、お答えすることは避けますのじゃ。明言することは避けさせていただきますのじゃ。
Well, I will avoid answering. I will refrain from making a clear statement, noja.
あの...
Um...
何も言わない。沈黙ですのじゃ。賢い、賢いわしは沈黙を
I will say nothing. It is silence, noja. Wise, wise me will choose...
選択いたしますのじゃ。
...silence, noja.
わしのコメント欄に放火魔がおりますのじゃ！
There is an arsonist in my comment section, noja!
あー、恐ろしいのじゃ。
Ah, terrifying, noja.
恐ろしいのじゃ。
Terrifying, noja.
Do you also have weights at home?
Okay. Do you also have weight at home?
重りが家にありますか？ないのじゃ。No, no, noja. No, no, noja.
"Do you also have weights at home?" I don't, noja. No, no, noja. No, no, noja.
答えは沈黙！
The answer is silence!
Yes. クラピカも言ってたのじゃ。
Yes. Kurapika said so too, noja.
沈黙が正しいですのじゃ。うん。
Silence is correct, noja. Yep.
ハンター試験クリアさせていただきますのじゃ。
I shall pass the Hunter Exam, noja.
a heavy bag
a heavy bag. 重いカバン。
a heavy bag. A heavy bag.
うん。
Yep.
These weights are heavy!
重り heavy じゃなかったらあんま意味ないのじゃ。
If weights aren't heavy, they don't make much sense, noja.
Can he lift those weights?
Can he... "Can he lift those weights?"
Lift って何？Can he lift those weights? と。持ち上げられるとかかな？lift。
What is "lift"? "Can he lift those weights?" Is it like "can he lift"? Lift.
持ち上げます。んー...
To lift. Hmm...
Can she play basketball too?
オッケー
Okay.
リフトが「持ち上げる」。リフトが「持ち上げる」。んー...
'Lift' means 'to lift up'. 'Lift' means 'to lift'. Hmm...
リフティング。リフティングって言うよね？
Lifting... We say 'lifting' in Japanese, right?
あの、サッカー、もしくはフットボールの、あの、あの、さ。ずっとボール浮かすやつ。あれリフティングって言う。
You know, in soccer, or football, where you keep bouncing the ball. We call that 'lifting'.
あれが「上げる」？んー...
Does that mean 'to lift' or raise? Hmm...
んーー...
Hmm...
やばい。「もしくは」って言ったのに「サッカー」って言われている。「もしくは」って言ったのに！「もしくは」って言ったの！
Oh no, they're correcting me with 'soccer' even though I said 'or'. But I said 'or'! I did say 'or'!
I said 'もしくは'! I said 'or'! I said 'or'! 言った！I said 'or' 言ったのじゃ！
I said 'or'! I said 'or'! I said 'or'! I said it! I said 'or'!
オッケー？うん。
Okay? Yes.
うん。こ、怖い。怖い。炎上怖いおじゃ。オッケー。オッケー、オッケー。
Yes. I-I'm scared. I'm scared. I'm afraid of getting canceled. Okay. Okay, okay.
あははは
Ahahaha!
I said 'or'! オッケー？Yes! うん。
I said 'or'! Okay? Yes! Yeah.
オッケー。
Okay.
Can Lisa surf well?
リサは上手にサーフィンできますか？
んー、んー、んー...
Hmm, hmm, hmm...
Do you lift weights at the gym?
ジムで重りを持ち上げますか？
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Can you do a push-up?
Can you do a push-up? What is push-up? 押してあげる？
Can you do a push-up? What is a push-up? To push and lift?
なんか、ジムのやつなのかな？筋トレのやつなのかな？
Is it a gym thing? Or a workout thing?
Can you throw a ball?
うん。メラは、メラは筋トレしない。
Yeah. Mela... Mela doesn't work out.
Do you lift, bro? I am not lift! 筋トレしない！
Do you lift, bro? I don't lift! I don't work out!
腕立て伏せ！Push-up is a gym exercise! へえー！
Push-up! 'Push-up is a gym exercise'! Ahh!
ジムの話。オッケー。
So it's about the gym. Okay.
Push-up, 腕立て伏せ。I, I can't push-up because it's hard. 難しいからしない。
Push-ups. I, I can't do push-ups because they're hard. They're difficult, so I don't do them.
うん。I actually I go gym, but I only walking.
Yeah. Actually, I go to the gym, but I only walk.
ウォーキングしかしないのじゃ。うん。
I only do walking. Yep.
ウォーキング。Just walking のじゃ。
Walking. Just walking.
うん。腕立て伏せ？
Yeah. Push-ups?
No even one push-up? あー...
Not even one push-up? Ah...
If anyone say me...
If anyone says to me...
「しろ」って言われたらするけど、
If someone tells me to, I will,
自主的にはしないのじゃ。
but I don't do them voluntarily.
うん。
Yeah.
Because it's hard. Too hard. Hard walk? I don't like hard walk のじゃ。うん。
Because it's hard. Too hard. Hard work? I don't like hard work. Yep.
うん。
Yeah.
How many miles do you walk? えー！マイル、マイルわからないのじゃ。
'How many miles do you walk?' Huh! Miles... I don't know miles.
あの、キロメーターでもいい？キロメーターでもいい？
Can we use kilometers instead? Is kilometers okay?
あの、5kmぐらい歩くのじゃ。うん。
I walk about 5 kilometers. Yep.
キロメーターぐらい歩く。のじゃ。
I walk about that many kilometers.
うん。
Yeah.
マイルがわからない。
I don't know miles.
1.6? 1.6kmが1マイル。
1.6? 1.6 kilometers is 1 mile.
じゃあ、大体アラウンド5マイル...
So that's around 5 miles...
ん？
Huh?
3、3.1マイル。3.1マイルぐらい歩く。
3, 3.1 miles. I walk about 3.1 miles.
のじゃ。
Yep.
うん。のじゃ。
Yeah. Yes.
あと、ジム。
And the gym.
のじゃ。
Yes.
Wow, can she do fifty push-ups? Wow!
Wow, wow! Can she do fifty push-ups?
50回も腕立て伏せできるのじゃ？すごい！それすごいのじゃ。
She can do fifty push-ups? Wow! That's amazing.
I can't do push-ups!
Yes, これ。This is me! This is me! I can't do push-ups! もう、できない。
Yes, this! This is me! This is me! 'I can't do push-ups!' I just can't do them.
えーっと、腕立て伏せができない。
Let's see, 'I can't do push-ups'.
I can't, because it's hard.
I can do five push-ups.
5回。まあ、5回なら...
Five times. Well, if it's five times...
Maybe I can do five. Maybe.
多分。Maybeね。うん。
Probably. Maybe, right? Yeah.
Can you swim?
Can you swim? Swim.
うん。
Yeah.
Push-ups are hard!
Yes, I think so, too! Push-up are hard. アップす？
Yes, I think so, too! 'Push-ups are hard.' 'Push-ups'?
「アプス」なんじゃね？「プッシュアップ」が1回じゃから、何回もやると「アプス」になるんじゃね？
It's 'push-ups', right? A single one is a 'push-up', so if you do it multiple times it becomes 'push-ups', right?
何回もやって's'になるから'are'なの？腕立て伏せはきつい。Yes, 腕立て伏せ。
Because it's plural with an 's', it takes 'are'? 'Push-ups are hard.' Yes, push-ups.
腕立て伏せはきつい
"Push-ups are hard."
Yes
うん、うん、うん
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
マルチプル
Multiple.
Tom can do...
twenty...
push-ups.
20回。トムは20回。
20 times. Tom does it 20 times.
うん
Yeah.
オッケー
Okay.
"Push-ups are hard." Yes, I think so too.
プッシュアップ名詞？プッシュアップ名詞なの？
Is "push-up" a noun? Is it a noun?
腹筋？ない。ノー腹筋。
Abs? None. No abs.
うん
Yeah.
うん、うん、うん、うん
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm...
プッシュアップっていう名詞だからs？名詞だからs？名詞だからsって何じゃ？
Plural "s" because "push-up" is a noun? What do you mean by that?
それ知らない。
I didn't know that.
腕立て伏せができない。 I...
"I can't do push-ups." I...
can't...
do...
push-ups.
うん
Yeah.
わあ、これ、Wow...
Wow, these...
these...
weights are...
heavy.
うん、heavy
Yeah, heavy.
ジムでウエイトを上げてますか？
"Do you lift weights at the gym?"
Are you... 違うか。
"Are you..." Wait, no.
あげるが、動詞だから "Do" なのか？
"Lift" is a verb, so is it "Do"?
Do you...
lift...
Do you lift...
weights...
at... Do you lift the...
weights at...
Do you lift weights...
at the gym?
どう？
How's that?
合ってる？何で合ってるか分かんない！Why? Why?
It's correct? I don't know why! Why? Why?
何で合ってるか分かんない！Why it is correct?
I don't know why it's right! Why is it correct?
わかんない。なんか適当にやったら当たった。
I don't know. I just guessed and got it right.
適当にやったら当たったのじゃ。
I just guessed and got it right.
Do you lift weights...
リフトが上げる。ウェイトを上げる。
"Lift" is "to raise." Raising weights.
"Plural so no 'the' necessary."
ウェイト。あ、sがあるから "the" がいらない？
Weights. Ah, because of the "s," "the" is not needed?
"You don't need to specify the object of the action."
うーん。
Hmm...
Plural noja. 複数形じゃない。
Plural noja. So it's plural.
ウェイト。
Weights.
特定の重みじゃない。"It's not specific weights. It's weights in general."
It's not specific weights. "It's not specific weights, it's weights in general."
確かに、ウェイトが、"the weights" だったら重みが限定されてろ。
Indeed, if it were "the weights," the weights would be specified.
かも。ウェイトにこだわりがない、確かに。
Maybe. It doesn't matter which weights, true.
ウェイトリフティング、"lift weights"、"any weights"、確かに、"any weights" だ。
Weightlifting... "lift weights," "any weights," yes, it means "any weights."
"any weights" だから、 "the" がいらない。
Since it's "any weights," "the" is not needed.
"Lift the weights/the weights both okay, but 'at gym' is wrong. 'At the gym' is right."
" 'Lift the weights/weights' are both okay, but 'at gym' is wrong. 'At the gym' is right."
Why? Why "at the gym" is right? なんで "at gym" が wrong?
Why? Why is "at the gym" right? Why is "at gym" wrong?
なんで？あの、そう、こっちもよく分かんない。"at gym" はダメ？Why?
Why? Yes, I don't really get this part either. Is "at gym" bad? Why?
なんで？
Why?
なんで "at the" なの？ "at gym" は no? Why?
Why is it "at the"? Is "at gym" a no? Why?
なんで "the gym" is place.
Why... "the gym is a place."
"the gym is place..." あ、"the gym" で一個なの？
"the gym is a place..." Oh, is "the gym" considered one thing?
ああ、"It's a specific gym." 確かに。
Ah, "It's a specific gym." Indeed.
"gym needs to be specific." 確かに。
"gym needs to be specific." True.
ジムは、どのジムか分からない。どの、確かに。
We wouldn't know which gym it is otherwise. True.
どのジムか分からないとダメかも。
Maybe we need to know which gym it is.
"the gym is specific place. 'at the gym' is right." 確かに。
"'the gym' is a specific place. 'at the gym' is right." Indeed.
確かに、そっか。じゃあ "the" を入れるところは
True, I see. So the place where we put "the" is...
指定しなきゃいけないとこ。指定しなきゃいけないとこは "the" がある。
...somewhere we have to specify. We use "the" for things we must specify.
どのジムか分からないと "a" でもいい？
If we don't know which gym, is "a" okay too?
え、ちなみに、a と the の違いって何？
Wait, by the way, what's the difference between "a" and "the"?
"What is the difference of the and a?"
"'the gym' and 'a gym' are okay." オッケー、オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
"'the gym' and 'a gym' are okay." Okay, okay, okay, okay.
分かってきた。
I'm starting to get it.
"'a' is one among many."
"'the' is specific one." あー。
"'the' is a specific one." Ah!
じゃあ、本当にさっき言ってた通りだ。
So, it's exactly what you guys were saying earlier.
なんでもいい時は "a"。よく分かんない時は "a"。
You use "a" when anything is fine, or when you don't really know.
よく分かんない時は "a" だけど、 "at a gym"
When you don't know, you use "a", so "at a gym"...
...だけど
But...
なんか、きっと何のジムか分かってるんじゃの？
I guess you probably know which gym it is, right?
何のジムか分かってると「the gym」
If you know which gym, it's "the gym."
「the」は
The...
「the」はspecific、あ、あの、specific
"The" is specific... Ah, that, specific.
どっかのジムに行く...。うーん。
Going to some gym... Hmm...
いろんなジムに行くなら、あ、
If you go to various gyms...
オッケー。Many many gyms に行く
Okay. If you go to many, many gyms,
なら「a」。
then it's "a."
「the」あの、
"The" is that...
「a」何か。
"a" is something.
うーん、あのジム。
Hmm... that gym.
じゃあ
So
「the」の方が使う？
do we use "the" more?
「その」とかがついてたら「the」。
If it has "that" or something, it's "the."
"Mastering articles is super important for English." I think so too.
でも、あんまりよく分からん。
But I don't really get it.
ランダムなチョコザップなら「a」。なるほど。
If it's a random Chocozap, it's "a." I see.
ランダムなチョコザップなら「a」だけど、チョコザップ〇〇店なら「the」。
If it's a random Chocozap, it's "a," but if it's the Chocozap [location] branch, it's "the."
おおー。
Oh...
「the」で特定。
"The" specifies it.
"I go to a gym on the weekend." You don't specify which gym. 確かに。
"I go to a gym on the weekend." You don't specify which gym. True.
じゃあ、あんまり仲良くない人には「a」？
Then, for people you're not very close with, is it "a"?
あんまり仲良くない、あの、知らない人には「a」。うーん。
For people you're not very close with, like strangers, it's "a." Hmm.
ふんふんふんふん。
Mhm, mhm.
"exactly, depends on how specific you are in the situation." 確かに。
"exactly, depends on how specific you are in the situation." True.
確かに。うーん。
True. Hmm.
"Both okay"
へえー。
Oh...
"I go to the gym, the other person understands which gym you're talking about."
ああー。"I go to the gym"
Ah, "I go to the gym"...
じゃあ、仲良い、
So, close friends,
遊び回りたメンバーに、
members I hang out with...
"I go to the gym"っていうのは、丸だけど、
saying "I go to the gym" is correct, but...
例えば、you guys, メラぐみ don't know
for example, you guys, Melagumi, don't know
where, what gym I go, じゃ。
which gym I go to, right?
メラぐみは、わしがどこのジムに行くか知らないじゃろう？
Melagumi, you don't know which gym I go to, right?
そう、メラぐみは、から、when I told メラぐみは、
Right, so when I tell Melagumi,
あの、"I go to a gym"
like, "I go to a gym"..."
そういうこと？
Is that it?
知らないよね。
You don't know, right?
知ってたら怖いやろう？知ってないじゃろう？知ってないじゃろう？
It'd be scary if you knew. You don't, right? You don't, right?
Maybe you guys don't know what, where gym, what gym I go, でしょう？
Maybe you guys don't know what, where gym, what gym I go to, right?
うん。知ってたら怖いのじゃ。オッケー、オッケー。
Yeah. It'd be scary if you knew. Okay, okay.
分かってきたのじゃ。
I'm starting to get it.
よしよしよし、オッケー、オッケー。I understand.
Alright, okay, okay. I understand.
ちょっと分かってきた。
I get it a bit now.
基本「the」のことが多いな。
Basically, it's mostly "the."
Maybe Duolingoの問題だったら
Maybe if it's a Duolingo question...
「the」の方が多い？
it's mostly "the"?
日常会話だと「the」の方が多い。話し相手が友達とかで。確かに。
In daily conversation, "the" is used more because you're talking to friends. True.
基本的に友達とか近い人間、一般用だと「the」が多い。Duolingoメタ。確かに。
Basically, with friends or close people, in general use, there are many "the"s. Duolingo meta. True.
うん、うん、うん。オッケー。
Yeah, yeah, mhm. Okay.
メラがどこのジムに行ってるか分からないけど、配信でよく出るなら、いつも話してくれている「あの」ジムねって意味で「the」がつくパターンもある。確かに。
Even if we don't know which gym Mela goes to, if it comes up often on stream, "the" can be used to mean "that" gym she always talks about. True.
確かに。わしがもしジムの話をめっちゃ配信でしたら、「ああ、なんかいつも話してるあのジムね」ってので、
True. If I talk about the gym a lot on stream, you'd think, "Ah, that gym she always talks about," so...
その具体的にどこの店舗かは分からないけど、メラがいつも話している共通認識の上の「あの」で「the」がつくのか。
even if you don't know the exact location, you use "the" for "that gym" based on our mutual understanding.
なるほどなるじゃ、オッケー、オッケー。分かった。
I see, I see. Okay, okay. I get it.
「the gym」の方が正しい。
"The gym" is more correct.
ジムは「the gym」の方が自然。オッケー、オッケー。
For gym, "the gym" is more natural. Okay, okay.
分かった、分かった。
I get it, I get it.
オッケー。
Okay.
ノーミスでクリア！やったのじゃ！
Cleared with zero mistakes! Yay!
分かってきた。
I'm starting to understand.
「a」と「the」はもっと難しい、イングリッシュ...
"A" and "the" are more difficult, English...
一瞬... 初心者にとって English beginner にとって "a" とか "the" とかはめっちゃ難しいから
For a moment... For beginners, like an English beginner, "a" or "the" is really difficult, so...
I do karate.
I do karate. 空手をします。空手をします。
I do karate. I do karate.
ふん、ふん、ふん。
Hmm, hmm, hmm.
Do you do yoga?
Do you do yoga? "Do you do" だって。Do が2個つくよ。Do 2個つく。"Do you do."
Do you do yoga? It says, "Do you do." There are two "Do"s. Two "Do"s. "Do you do."
ダンスロボットダンスや。Do you do yoga? あなたはヨガをしますか？ヨガをしますか。
Just like Dance Robot Dance. "Do you do yoga?" "Do you do yoga?" "Do you do yoga?"
うん、うん、うん。
Yes, yes, yes.
うん、うん。街に1つしかないような建物なら the。役所的な。役所とか。
Hmm, hmm. If it's a unique building in town, it's "the." Like a city hall. Or a public office.
セブンイレブンは the で、いつものセブンイレブンは "a"？
Is Seven-Eleven "the," and the usual Seven-Eleven "a"?
いつものセブンイレブンが the なんじゃない？大体...で、広く取るセブンイレブンが "a" なんじゃない？
Isn't the usual Seven-Eleven "the"? And a generic Seven-Eleven is "a"?
文脈によるな。文脈によらない？それも。
It depends on the context. Doesn't it depend on the context? That too.
なんかさ、例えばコンビニの中でセブンイレブンを指定するなら the だけど、
For example, if you specify a Seven-Eleven among convenience stores, it's "the," but...
セブンイレブンの中で、もっと細かいものの話をするなら "a" の時もない？
...if you're talking about something more specific inside a Seven-Eleven, isn't there a time when it's "a"?
なんか文脈によって変わるのじゃ。なんか内容... 内容によって変わらない？
It changes depending on the context. Doesn't it change depending on the content?
その、その時話したい内容によって変わるのじゃ。わー、難しい！
It changes depending on what you want to talk about at that time. Wow, that's difficult!
奥が深いのじゃ。いつものセブンの聞き手が知らないなら...
It's so deep. If the listener doesn't know your usual Seven-Eleven...
ええー、奥が深いのじゃ。うん、うん、うん、うん。
Wow, it's so deep. Hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm.
My karate class is at seven.
class. My... 空手のクラスは、空手教室は7時から。
class. My... Karate class, the karate class is at seven.
My karate class is at seven. うん、うん。
My karate class is at seven. Hmm, hmm.
7時に空手。ちなみにわしも空手習ってたことあるのじゃ。
Karate at seven. By the way, I used to take karate lessons too.
空手。ある。のじゃ。
Karate. I did. Yes.
My cats do yoga too.
のじゃ？My cats do yoga too. キャットも？
What? My cats do yoga too. Cats too?
キャットも、キャットもヨガとかするのじゃ？
Do cats, do cats do yoga too?
My cats do yoga too.
のじゃ。うーーん。
Yes. Hmm.
うん、帯はね、全然、帯ね、白帯のまま終わったのじゃ。あのね、すぐ、すぐ終わったのじゃ。
Well, my belt... I ended up staying a white belt. You see, it ended quickly, very quickly.
あのね、何でね、why I, uh, practice karate かというとね、
You see, as for why I, uh, practice karate, well...
あの、ストロングガールに憧れたのじゃ。ストロングガール is so cool でしょ？そう。
...I admired strong girls. A strong girl is so cool, right? Yes.
ストロングサラマンダー is so cool でしょ？だから、I want to be strong.
A strong salamander is so cool, right? So, I want to be strong.
強くたなりたかったんじゃが、強くなりたかったんじゃが、から空手を習ったんだけど、
I wanted to become strong, I wanted to become strong, so I took karate, but...
空手って戦う空手と、あの型の空手があるのじゃ。
In karate, there's fighting karate and "kata" (form) karate.
うん、なんか、だ、ダンスみたいな。
Yes, it's like... like dancing.
なんかダンスみたいな覚えゲーの空手があって、わしがね、習ってたのが、
There's a karate that's like a memorization game, like dancing, and the one I took was...
覚えゲーの空手なんじゃよ。そう、覚えゲーのやつ。
...that memorization game karate. Yes, the memorization one.
なんか、あの、戦う空手が習いたかったのに、あの、いざ教室に入ってみたら、
I wanted to learn fighting karate, but once I joined the class...
なんか、あの、なんじゃっけ？平安初段みたいな、そういうなんか、覚え、覚え空手。
...it was like... what was it? Heian Shodan... that kind of memorization karate.
覚え空手の方に配属されて、あはははは！
I was assigned to the memorization karate class, hahaha!
覚え空手の方に配属されて、え、わしが思ってたのと違うと思って、
I was assigned to the memorization karate, and I thought, "Eh, this is different from what I expected."
そう、思ってたのと違うと思って、そう、思ってたのと違ってやめたのじゃ。うん。うん。
Yes, it was different from what I thought, so I quit because it was different. Yes. Yes.
わし本当は、わし本当はあの、戦いたかった。I want to fight. Fight ストロング空手をしたかったんじゃが、
Actually, I really wanted to fight. I want to fight. I wanted to do fighting, strong karate, but...
うん、なんかあの、型、型の方にね、配属された。うん。
...I was assigned to the "kata" (form) side. Yes.
それで、すごく、あの、悲しかった。そう、I'm sad. そう、で、やめた。
So, I was really sad. Yes, I'm sad. So, I quit.
そう、やめたのじゃ。なんか思ってたのと違ったのじゃ。Yes. うん。
Yes, I quit. It was different from what I expected. Yes. Hmm.
これじゃないって言えばよかった？なんかなんか、せっかく、え、自分がやりたいって言ってさ、
Should I have said "This isn't it"? Well, after I said I wanted to do it...
習い事通わせてくれたのにさ、いや、なんかこれじゃなくて戦うのがやりたかったのじゃって言うとちょっと、
...and they let me take lessons, saying "No, I didn't want this, I wanted to fight" would be a bit...
ちょっとあの、やっぱ子供ながらにやっぱ、長生きしてるからさ、
...As a child, but since I've lived a long time...
あの、わしがさ、その、人間低学年の頃もさ、すでにさ、もう何百歳じゃったからさ、
...Even when I was in lower grades as a human, I was already hundreds of years old, so...
変にさ、大人でさ、変に自分は大人じゃったからさ、言い、言いづらくて。
...I was strangely adult-like, strangely mature, and it was hard to say.
そう、せっかく、せっかく習わせてくれたのに、ちょっと言うの違うかなと思って、
Yes, they went out of their way to let me take lessons, so I thought it would be wrong to say it...
そう、言い出せなかったのじゃ。言い出せなくてやめたのじゃ。のじゃ。うん。
...and I couldn't bring myself to say it. I quit because I couldn't say it. Yes. Hmm.
Yes. This is my 空手 の思い出、のじゃ。Yes.
Yes. This is my memory of karate. Yes.
よし。
Alright.
Where can we do yoga?
でも思うけど、子供はあん、気なんて使わなくていいのじゃ、本当は。本来ね。
But I think kids shouldn't have to worry about being considerate, actually. Originally, you know.
本来子どもは気を使わずにやりたいことを主張していくべきなのじゃ。
Originally, children should assert what they want to do without worrying about others.
なぜなら、幼少期にやりたいことを主張できないと、大人になるともっとできなくなって、
Because if you can't assert what you want during childhood, you'll find it even harder as an adult,
いずれそれが自分の首を絞めることになるからなのじゃ。わかるのじゃ、わし。
and eventually, it will end up strangling you. I understand this very well.
わしは分かっておるのじゃ。
I do understand.
じゃから、わがままになってみるのも大事なのじゃ。
That's why it's also important to try being selfish.
でもわがままになれる環境となれない環境ってのもあって、結構、あの、
But there are environments where you can be selfish and ones where you can't, and actually, um...
お家によってはね、わがままに主張ができないところもあるから、それもまた難しい話じゃなって思うのじゃ。
depending on the household, there are places where you can't make selfish demands, so I think that's also a difficult issue.
うー、のじゃ。
Mmh, indeed.
環境によるのじゃ。
It depends on the environment.
いつかわがままが言える環境におぬしが出会えるといいなって、思いもするのじゃ。
I also hope you'll someday find an environment where you can speak your mind.
Where...
Where can we do yoga?
どこでヨガをやりますか？
"Where do we do yoga?"
文のパターンね。えーっと、これはパターンは、
The sentence pattern, right? Um, the pattern is...
Whereとか疑問のWが文頭にあって、はてながあるやつ。
...the one with "Where" or other question words starting with 'W' at the beginning, ending with a question mark.
When can they join us?
のじゃ。When can they join us?
Noja. "When can they join us?"
うん。オッケー。
Yeah, okay.
Yes, you can watch.
あなたは見れます…はい。
"You can watch..." Yes.
見てもいいよ。
"You can watch it."
"You can watch it~"
When can we meet?
いつわしたち会えるのじゃ？
"When can we meet?"
When can we meet? メラぐみ。
"When can we meet?" Melagumi!
メラぐみ、メラぐみ、When can we meet? いつ会えるのじゃ？
Melagumi, Melagumi, "When can we meet?" When can we meet?
Yes, your friend can join us.
友達も一緒に参加できます。
"Your friend can also join us."
We can play from five to six.
We can play from five to six. 5時から6時の間に遊べます。
"We can play from five to six." We can play between 5 and 6 o'clock.
5時から6時まで一緒に遊べる。
We can play together from 5 to 6.
She does karate from four to five.
ちょうどでも、Just now 確かに。今も会ってる。
Wait, but "just now", indeed. We are meeting now too.
Just now we are meeting, noja. Yes. 確かに。
"Just now we are meeting", indeed. Yes. Exactly.
ストリーミングで会ってるのじゃ。Yes. えー
We are meeting through streaming. Yes. Um...
She does karate from four to five.
1時間、4時から5時まで空手をやってます。She does.
For one hour, she does karate from 4 to 5. "She does."
Sheだからdoesなのじゃ。
Because it's "She", it's "does", you see.
Yes, we are meeting now. Yes, we are online. Online meeting now.
オッケー。
Okay.
When can we practice... practice...
"When can we practice..." Mela: "practice..."
When can we practice karate?
Where can I play...
can、人間、動詞。オッケー。
"Can", person, verb. Okay.
Where can I play tennis? どこでテニス遊べますか？
"Where can I play tennis?" Where can we play tennis?
karate classes
karate classes. 空手教室。
"Karate classes." Karate class.
あーー
Ahhh~
I do yoga everyday.
"I do yoga every day."
うん。ヨガ。
Yeah. Yoga.
When can we do karate?
from five to seven. いつ空手やる？5、7時。
"From five to seven." When do we do karate? 5 to 7.
5時ー7時。
5 to 7.
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
一緒に空手ができる。
"We can do karate together."
We can... ん？
We can... Hm?
We can. canの後はdo。We can do karate...
We can. After "can" is "do". "We can do karate..."
together. じゃない？
"...together", isn't it?
We can do karate together. canの後はdoesじゃない。do. do. Sつかない。
"We can do karate together." After "can" is not "does", it's "do". Do, do. No "s".
Sつかない。
No "s" added.
どこで空手ができますか？Where...
"Where can you do karate?" Where...
Where can...
ん？Where can...
Hm? "Where can..."
do karate.
のじゃ？あ、人間を
Noja? Ah, the person...
人間を指定しなきゃいけない。
You have to specify the person.
I have to... 人間、they。何か入れなきゃいけない。
I have to... The person is "they". I have to put something there.
Where can they do karate?
誰が空手をするか、入れなきゃいけない。
You have to specify who does karate.
Very close, close. 確かに主語がない。主語がない。
Very close, close. Indeed, there's no subject. There's no subject.
確かに
Indeed.
theyなんだね。
Ah, it's "they."
It's "they."
Yes, you were missing about, missing a subject! Subject?
Yes, you were missing... missing a subject! Subject?
サブジェクトがいる。
I need a subject.
Yeah, we need a subject. Okay.
で、サブジェクトが "they"
And the subject is "they."
うーん、Where can they... 誰が？かがいる。
Hmm... "Where can they..." Who is needed?
"who"がいる。do karate? Okay. わかった。
We need "who." "...do karate?" Okay, I got it.
サブジェクトがいる。
I need a subject.
サブジェクト、who, what. Okay. who, what.
Subject... who, what. Okay, who, what.
ふむふむふむ。
I see, I see.
"Where can do karate" is "who are you talking about, they?"
んー、who or...なるほど。
Hmm, "who" or... I see.
they.
Okay. 私たちは9時から10時まで遊びます。
Okay. "We play from nine to ten."
あ、We! サブジェクト！サブジェクト！
Ah, we! Subject! Subject!
You guys is subject, We is subject.
"You guys" is the subject, "we" is the subject.
We...
play.
うーーー
Uhhh...
from...? We play from... 10...
from...? We play from... ten...
ん？nine to ten!
Huh? "nine to ten!"
うん。
Yeah.
"It needs the subject I, we, they, he, she." メラ教わりました。うーん、いっぱい。
"It needs the subject I, we, they, he, she." Mela learned. Hmm, so many.
守護、サブジェクトがいる。Okay, subjects.
Subject... I need a subject. Okay, subjects.
Okay.
どこで空手ができますか？えーっと、
"Where can they do karate?" Uh...
Where can...
they, サブジェクト！ they...
they, the subject! They...
do karate?
Where can they do, サブジェクト。
"Where can they do," subject.
Okay! サブジェクトのじゃ。theyが入った。 Okay.
Okay! Subject, noja! "They" went in. Okay.
うん、Okay.
Yeah, okay.
やったのじゃーー！
I did it!
"It also a subject."
ふむふむふむ。Okay, okay, okay, okay. わかった。
I see, I see, I see. Okay, okay, okay, okay. I get it.
わかってきた。Okay.
I'm starting to understand. Okay.
サブジェクト、is、大切。
Subject is important.
果物、Fruit!
Fruit, "fruit!"
Okay. "I eat lots of fruit."
え、果物をたくさん食べます。
Uh, "I eat lots of fruit."
あ、サラマンダーイズ、
Ah, "Salamanders..."
サラマンダー don't eat fruits. うん。
Salamanders don't eat fruit. Yeah.
サラマンダーは、フルーツ苦手。
Salamanders are not good with fruit.
"Japanese assumes you know the subject so they don't say it." 日本語確かに言わないかも。
"Japanese assumes you know the subject so they don't say it." In Japanese, indeed, we might not say it.
うん、Mela don't eat fruit actually. Yes.
Yeah, Mela doesn't eat fruit actually. Yes.
Yes. Yes, 偏食。I'm ね、I'm 偏食なのじゃ。
Yes. Yes, picky eater. I'm... I'm a picky eater, you see.
No fruits. うん。苦手。
No fruits. Yeah. I don't like it.
"Do you like sweets?" スイーツは好き。スイーツは好き。スナック好き！
"Do you like sweets?" I like sweets. I like sweets. I like snacks!
I really like snacks but, I don't like fruit. うん。
I really like snacks, but I don't like fruit. Yeah.
うん、フルーツ。
Yeah, fruit.
"Bad girl?" Yes, I'm a bad girl!
うん、好き嫌い。
Yeah, picky about food.
"How about vegetables?" Salamander don't eat vegetables! Yes.
"How about vegetables?" Salamanders don't eat vegetables! Yes.
Salamander don't eat vegetables and fruits. うん。
Salamanders don't eat vegetables and fruit. Yeah.
No, no vegetables. No vegetables.
No vegetables. Yes.
"Too cute to be bad?" Yes, cuteだからOkay! CuteだからOkay!
"Too cute to be bad?" Yes, because I'm cute, it's okay! Because I'm cute, it's okay!
うん、Yes. I only eat 肉！肉！肉！
Yeah, yes. I only eat meat! Meat! Meat!
"What do you eat?"
Meat! 肉！焼肉！Yes.
Meat! Meat! Yakiniku! Yes.
肉！
Meat!
No, no salad. Only meat, yes. Only meat!
Only meat!
野菜ジュースは、ギリ。野菜ジュースは飲める。
Vegetable juice is barely okay. I can drink vegetable juice.
うん、野菜ジュースは飲める。でも野菜ジュースが飲めるギリギリの野菜。Yes.
Yeah, I can drink vegetable juice. But vegetable juice is the bare minimum of vegetables I can take. Yes.
"Do you cook it yourself with fire?" No, because my fire is too hot!
My fire is, あの、so, temperatureが...
My fire is... you know, so, the temperature is...
めっちゃはい。あの、燃えてなくなっちゃう、あの、even...
Yes, totally. It'll burn and disappear, uh, even...
I cook with my fire?
わしの炎で料理したら、あの、なくなる。うん。
If I cook with my fire, it'll disappear. Yeah.
なくなっちゃう。Very hot. It's blue fire. Yes, blue flame. It's super hot. Yes, super hot.
It'll disappear. Very hot. It's blue fire. Yes, blue flame. It's super hot. Yes, super hot.
What about donuts, like kiyoko? Yes, I love donuts! I love donuts. Hmm.
What about donuts, like kiyoko? Yes, I love donuts! I love donuts. Yeah.
そう。Become charcoal? Yes, charcoal.
Right. Become charcoal? Yes, charcoal.
そう、炭になっちゃう。
Yeah, it turns into charcoal.
Tomato? No tomato!
Yes ketchup. I can eat ketchup but I can't eat tomato. Hmm.
Yes, ketchup. I can eat ketchup, but I can't eat tomatoes. Yeah.
So carb? So carb and meat only? Yes! I... I love rice.
So carbs? So carbs and meat only? Yes! I... I love rice.
ライス好き。But...
I like rice. But...
No... tomato, no tomato, no vegetables.
Yes ketchup. Hmm. Ketchup is okay.
Yes, ketchup. Yeah, ketchup is okay.
Yes.
あと、Mela, do you like fish dishes? んーと、little.
And... \"Mela, do you like fish dishes?\" Hmm, a little.
I like salmon! サーモン好きのじゃ。
I like salmon! I like salmon, noja.
サーモンは好き。
I like salmon.
Ketchup or tomato in pasta? Ketchup!
ケチャップ、I like ketchup. Hmm. Hmm.
Ketchup, I like ketchup. Yeah. Yeah.
サーモン可愛いけど、サーモン好き。
Salmon are cute, but I like salmon.
江戸で何食べてたか？魚！Fish and rice!
What did I eat in Edo? Fish! Fish and rice!
魚食べてたのじゃ。のじゃ。
I was eating fish, noja. Noja.
Pizza? Pizza 好き？Mela like pizza? Yes! I... I like pepperoni! Pepperoni pizza!
Pizza? Do you like pizza? \"Mela like pizza?\" Yes! I... I like pepperoni! Pepperoni pizza!
うん、ピザ好き。
Yeah, I like pizza.
ピザ好き。Yes. Hmm.
I like pizza. Yes. Yeah.
トースト好き。トースト好き。
I like toast. I like toast.
うん、ペパロニピザ好き。
Yeah, I like pepperoni pizza.
Because, why? Okay. Oh, I... I talk about why I like pepperoni pizza. Because, pepperoni pizza は野菜入ってない。
Because, why? Okay. Oh, I... I'll talk about why I like pepperoni pizza. Because, pepperoni pizza doesn't have vegetables.
そう、pepperoni pizza is だいたい no vegetables じゃない？
Right, pepperoni pizza is mostly no vegetables, right?
あの、マルゲリータとかは野菜あるじゃん？Tomato とかあるじゃん？But pepperoni pizza is
Like, Margherita has vegetables, right? It has tomatoes, right? But pepperoni pizza is...
あの、no vegetables. No veggies. Yes.
uh, no vegetables. No veggies. Yes.
そう、から、I can eat. No onion. No onion. Hmm.
So, because of that, I can eat it. No onions. No onions. Yeah.
そう、ペパロニピザはないから食べれる。そう。Oh, yes. Oh, yes yes yes.
Right, pepperoni pizza doesn't have them, so I can eat it. Right. Oh, yes. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
マルゲリータたまにトマト入ってるのじゃ。そう。うん。
Margherita sometimes has tomatoes, noja. Right. Yeah.
玉ねぎペパロニピザ入ってなくない？
Don't pepperoni pizzas usually not have onions?
ペパロニピ、ペパロニピザのトマトはケチャップなのじゃ。うん。うん。
The tomato in pepperoni pizza is ketchup, noja. Yeah. Yeah.
パイナップルは、あの、フルーツだからいけない。あの、ピザにパイナップルとかそういうのじゃなくてそもそも
Pineapple is, well, it's a fruit, so it's a no-go. It's not about pineapple on pizza or anything like that, but basically...
I can't eat pineapple because pineapple is fruits. I can't eat fruits. Hmm. Hmm.
I can't eat pineapple because pineapple is a fruit. I can't eat fruits. Yeah. Yeah.
Yes. I can't eat vegetable, noja. Yes.
Yes. I can't eat vegetables, noja. Yes.
フルーツ、no fruits, noja. Hmm. Hmm.
Fruits, no fruits, noja. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Okay. Hmm. No fruits. No fruits.
Okay. Okay. Yeah. No fruits. No fruits.
Can't or don't like? Don't like. I don't like fruits and vegetables.
イチゴもあんま好きじゃないけど、ケーキにのってるイチゴはギリ食べれるのじゃ。うん。
I don't really like strawberries either, but I can barely eat the strawberries on cakes, noja. Yeah.
確かにフルーツ食べれるの、アレルギーっぽい。アレルギーはないのじゃ。多分ないと思うのじゃ。うん。うん。うん。Yes.
\"Indeed, if you can't eat fruits, it sounds like an allergy.\" I don't have allergies, noja. I don't think I do, noja. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yes.
ガキメラ？えー、でも、まあサラマンダーは偏食なのじゃ。イチゴ大福食べれないのじゃ。I can't eat イチゴ。I don't like イチゴ大福。うん。よし、英語やるのじゃ。
\"Gaki Mela?\" Eh, well, salamanders are picky eaters, noja. I can't eat strawberry daifuku. I can't eat strawberries. I don't like strawberry daifuku. Yeah. All right, let's do English, noja.
ちょ、食べ物の話しちゃった。
Oops, I ended up talking about food.
たくさんの、a lot of? a lot of?
"Taku-san no" (lots of)... "a lot of"? "a lot of"?
Can I drink this water?
この水、飲んでも、いいですか？
Is it okay to drink this water?
ガキのじゃ？まい、食べられないもの、好き嫌いが多すぎるから、こっちサラマンダー偏食。事実ですのじゃ。イエス。
Kid, noja? My... because I have too many likes and dislikes of things I can't eat, this salamander is a picky eater. That is indeed a fact, noja. Yes.
Okay, and can I eat bread?
パン食べてもいいのじゃ？イエス。
Is it okay to eat bread? Yes.
When can you start the class?
When can you start the class? いつ授業を始められますか？
When can you start the class? When can you start the class?
好き嫌いもありそう。結構食べてるけどな。結構食べてるけど。
I do seem to have likes and dislikes. But I eat quite a lot, actually. I eat quite a lot.
How can I feel better?
どうすれば、どうしたら気分が良くなりますか？
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy.
のじゃ！
Noja!
そうなん？パンケーキヘルシーじゃないって！
Really?! They say pancakes aren't healthy!
マックス、パンケーキは健康に良くない。
Max, pancakes are not healthy.
Really?!
I... I thought pancake...
is healthy. Why?!
のじゃ。あれ？違う。
Noja. Oh, wait, that's wrong.
あ、いいやが入るのか。No, Noが入ってないのか。
Ah, "iya" (no) goes there. Oh, "No" isn't in there.
Sorry, Noを忘れてた。いや。
Sorry, I forgot "No". "Iya".
I forgot to... いや。Noを忘れてた。
I forgot to... "iya". I forgot "No".
のじゃ、I really like pancakes! I really like pancakes and I eat...
Noja, I really like pancakes! I really like pancakes and I eat...
ate... yesterday.
昨日食べた。そう。
I ate them yesterday. Yes.
My momが作ったパンケーキ食べたのじゃ。
My mom made pancakes and I ate them, noja.
うーん。
Yeah.
Mela, but what about tangerines?
みかんは食べられる。みかん好き。
I can eat tangerines. I like tangerines.
Sugar, I like sugar!
I really like sugar!
Yes, Mela like sweet stuff, yes! I really like sweet stuff!
Yes, Mela likes sweet stuff, yes! I really like sweet stuff!
好きなんのじゃ。
I love them, noja.
いや、お母さんと一緒に住んでないのじゃ、まい。
No, I don't live with my mom, my...
あー、あいる、一人暮らしだけど、My momが、あのー、
Ah, I live alone, but my mom, well,
あの、My houseに来て、クッキングしてくれる。作って、あのー、
she comes to my house and cooks for me. She makes, well,
なんじゃ？冷凍してくれる。
what is it? She freezes them for me.
冷凍してくれるご飯をね、作ってね、置いてってくれるのじゃ。
She makes meals that can be frozen and leaves them for me, noja.
そう。
Yes.
そう。お掃除とかもしてくれる。
Yes. She also does things like cleaning.
そう。優しいのじゃ。
Yes. She's so kind, noja.
Yes, really kind mom, dad...
yes.
お世話されてるのじゃ。うーん。イエス。
I'm being taken care of, noja. Yes.
クッキー作ってくれた。この前、My momがディアマンクッキー作ってくれたのじゃ。
She made cookies. The other day, my mom made diamant cookies for me, noja.
うーん。
Yeah.
My momね、ケーキとかもね、作ってくれる。
My mom also makes cakes and things for me.
優しいのじゃ。イエス。
She is so kind, noja. Yes.
Yeah, really kind, kind mom noja.
うーん。優しい。
Yes, she's kind.
あ、and also My mom, My mother is doing Duolingo.
Oh, and also my mom, my mother is doing Duolingo.
My mother really like Duolingo. 毎日してる。
My mother really likes Duolingo. She does it every day.
そう、わしのね、あの、母、My mother、マムがね、デュオリンゴをね、
Yes, my, well, my mother, my mother, Mom is doing Duolingo,
しててね、毎日しててね、全部クリアしちゃったらしい。
and she does it every day, and apparently she cleared all of it.
My mom, My momね、clear Duolingo, every, every lesson.
My mom, my mom, clear Duolingo, every, every lesson.
全部レクソンやっちゃったっぽくてね。そう。
It seems she did all of the lessons. Yes.
Mela's motherはね、あの、全部、全クリしてね、
Mela's mother, you see, she cleared all of them,
デュオリンゴ全クリしたっぽくてね、で、今ね、あの、日本語？
she apparently 100% cleared Duolingo, and now, Japanese?
デュオリンゴっていろんな言語を学べるんじゃが、あの、日本語？なんじゃ？
You can learn various languages on Duolingo, but Japanese? What is it?
わし今、イングリッシュ学んでるじゃろ？I'm learning English right now, but My mother,
Right now I'm learning English, right? I'm learning English right now, but my mother,
learning English with Duolingo complete?
Completeしたから、あの、My motherは今、
Because she completed it, my mother is now...
あの、日本語を英語で学んでるのじゃ。
she is learning Japanese in English, noja.
My mother is learning Japanese with...
イングリッシュ？
English?
そう、もう…
Yeah, she already...
そう、全部やっちゃったから、なんか、
completed all of it, like...
そう、英語の… 英語で日本語を学んでて、で、なんか、
Yeah, she's studying Japanese in English, and like...
Duolingoって、なんか、いろんな正解があるじゃろ？
Duolingo has various correct answers, right?
こういう言い方もできるよね、みたいな正解があるっぽくて、
It seems there are other correct phrasing options,
それをなんか申告してるらしい。
and she apparently reports them.
Duolingoに「こういうのもあります」みたいなのを申告して、
She reports things like, "This is also correct" to Duolingo...
申告してそれが通ると、なんかメールで「あなたの申告が通りました」みたいのが来るっぽくて、
and if it gets accepted, she gets an email saying, "Your report has been accepted" or something.
そう。それをやってるっぽい。そう。
Yeah, it seems she's doing that. Yeah.
そう、言語を英語に設定して、日本語コースをね、学んでるっぽいのじゃ。
Yeah, she sets her language to English and is studying the Japanese course, it seems.
そう。そう。
Yeah. Yeah.
ての、マイマムがやってる、ての、この前教えてくれた。
My mum is doing that, she told me about it recently.
わしがDuolingo始めたっつったら、「やってるよ」って。
When I said I started Duolingo, she said, "I'm doing it too."
うん。実家に帰ると母がね、たまにね、Duolingoやってるのじゃ。
Yeah. When I go back to my parents' house, my mother sometimes plays Duolingo.
うん、マイマム、Duolingoやってる。うん。
Yeah, my mum plays Duolingo. Yeah.
そう。母に英語習った方がいい、確かに。
Yeah. "You should learn English from your mother," indeed.
マイマザーはね、わしより英語できる。
My mother is better at English than me.
うん。わしより英語できるし、
Yeah. She's better at English than me, and...
マイマザー、マムも、マイダッドも、英語ペラペラ、ペラペラ？
my mother, mum, and dad are fluent in English. Fluent?
ペラペラ… マイダッドは英語喋れる。
Fluent... Well, my dad can speak English.
My dad can speak English.
My mumも、maybe, can speak English.
My mum too, maybe, can speak English.
I amちょっと… I am little. I am little.
I am a bit... I'm a little. I'm a little.
のじゃ。そう。わしよりできる。父と母はわしよりできる。
Yeah. They're better than me. Both my dad and mom are better than me.
Eat healthy meals.
健康的な食事を取りなさい。うん。
"Eat healthy meals." Yeah.
Yes.
のじゃ。そう。
Yeah. Right.
食事
Meal.
ミール。ミール。
Meal. Meal.
健康的な食事を食べ… わしに言ってるの？
"Eat healthy meals"... Are you telling me that?
I can't... because I like sugar.
I like sugar, I like snacks, I like sweets, のじゃ！
I like sugar, I like snacks, I like sweets! Yes!
Don't eat lots of sugar.
盗聴されてる！盗聴されてる！
I'm being wiretapped! I'm being wiretapped!
今、今わしの、わしの頭の中が盗聴されてるのじゃ！配信聞かれてるのじゃ！
Right now, my mind is being wiretapped! They are listening to my stream!
Don't eat lots of sugarって言われてる！Why? だめ？
They're telling me, "Don't eat lots of sugar"! Why? Is it bad?
Sugarだめ？ I really like sugar. だめ？ だめのじゃ？
No sugar? I really like sugar. Is it bad? No go?
Don't eat lots of sugar.
自分で言わされてるのじゃ。のじゃー。
I'm being made to say it myself. Oh no.
盗聴されてる。のじゃ。
I'm being wiretapped. Yeah.
Yes, ...
vegetables
Yes, vegetables are very healthy for you.
I know! 知ってる！知ってるけど！Yes.
I know! I know! I know, but! Yes.
知ってるけど！
I know, but!
a big meal
あ、聞こ…
Oh, I heard...
A big meal.
A big meal. 知ってるけどー！
A big meal. I know, but...!
Can you eat that big meal?
Can you eat that big meal? Yes, I can!
はい。
Yes.
渡る、Cross. 道、Road. 橋、Bridge. たくさんの、Lots of. 招待する、Invite.
Cross, cross. Road, road. Bridge, bridge. Lots of, lots of. Invite, invite.
のじゃ！
Yes!
Lots of food.
Lots of food. たくさんの食べ物、うむ。
Lots of food. Lots of food, yep.
I often ...
cook my meals at home.
自炊もします、のじゃ。Yes.
I also cook for myself. Yes.
のじゃ。
Yeah.
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃー！のじゃー！
No way! No way!
Pancakes is healthy!
Pancakes are healthy!
パンケーキは健康的じゃ… のじゃー！
"Pancakes are not healthy"... No way!
のじゃー！唐揚げ何もかけないのじゃ！
No way! I don't put anything on fried chicken!
Pancakes are healthy!
ヘルシーのじゃ！あ、マックス。
They're healthy! Oh, Max.
いや、マックス、パンケーキは…
No, Max, pancakes are...
パンケーキは、健康に…じゃない。
Pancakes are... not healthy.
What?!
Pancake is healthy!
のじゃあ…
Noja...
これは、あ、レッスン 6/6 だから…
Oh, this is lesson 6/6, so...
今日はこのレッスンで終わりにしよう。
let's finish with this lesson today.
今日はこれで終わり。
That's it for today.
これをやっておしまい。このレベルを一気に振り返ってみよう。
I'll do this and be done. "Let's review this level all at once!"
They are yummy, but not healthy. Sadly. Sadly?
初めて聞いた、Sadly。
That's the first time I've heard "sadly".
のじゃあ。
Noja.
ヘルシーじゃない。Pancakes are so yummy!
Not healthy. Pancakes are so yummy!
No, Max. Pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃ！また言われた！また…
Noja! They said it again! Again...
Sadly! Sadly か！Sadly.
Sadly! Ah, it means "sadly"! Sadly.
Sadly か。悲しいことに。あ、いやいや、Sadly. Okay, okay.
Sadly. "Sadly" as in "unfortunately". Oh, okay, okay, sadly.
ねえ、What? 何？
Hey, what? What?
Duolingo, 何のじゃ？
Duolingo, what are you doing, noja?
Pancake is healthy!
Pancakes are not that unhealthy by themselves...
It's usually the sugar, syrup or jam you have on top that carry that idea. 確かに！
"...It's usually the sugar, syrup or jam you have on top that carry that idea." True!
はい。
Yes.
チョコレートシロップをね、パンケーキにね、かける。
I put chocolate syrup on my pancakes.
Really yummy, のじゃ。
It's really yummy, noja.
Okay.
いや、マックス、パンケーキは健康にじゃない。
"No Max, pancakes are not healthy."
のじゃーーーー！
Nojaaaa!
メープルシロップ、まあ、食べる。食べるが…
Maple syrup... Well, I eat it. I do eat it, but...
I like チョコレートシロップの方が好き。
I like chocolate syrup better.
More than chocolate... Better than, のじゃ？
More than chocolate... "Better than", noja?
チョコレートシロップの方が、もっと好き。
I like chocolate syrup much more.
もっと好きのじゃ。
I like it more, noja.
ホイップクリームは好き。I like ホイップクリーム。
I like whipped cream. I like whipped cream.
Do you put whipped cream on it? えっと…
Do you put whipped cream on it? Well...
When I eat pancake in my house...
When I eat pancakes in my house...
家で食べる時はのせない。Only chocolate syrup.
I don't put it on when I eat at home. Only chocolate syrup.
"Better than." "More than" is correct, but lots of people say "better than".
I like chocolate syrup better than maple syrup.
Yes, you like chocolate more than maple syrup. Yes, yes, yes.
のじゃね。
Noja ne.
どこで空手ができますか？
"Where can they do karate?"
Where they... they... they...
えっと、サブジェクトみたいなやつ。サブジェクト。
Um, the thing like the subject. The subject.
Where they can do karate.
Yes?
ういっ、違う、違う。
Wait! No, that's wrong.
Where they can... 疑問系だから？
Where they can... Is it because it's a question?
Because it's 質問、question? Questionじゃから can they. あー！
Because it's a question? Since it's a question, it's "can they"! Ah!
疑問、確かに。Canが先だ。Questionだから。
A question, indeed. "Can" comes first because it's a question.
さっき聞いてたのに。
And yet I just listened to it earlier.
さっき聞いてた問題がいけなくなる理由教えてあげようか？
Shall I tell you why I mess up on questions I just heard?
あの、勘でやってるから。
It's because I'm doing them by guessing.
なんか学習というか、多分ノリでやってるから because さっきやってたのがいけなくなる。
It's not really learning, I'm probably just going with the flow, which is why I mess up on previous ones.
Okay, question.
Wow, you read fast!
わあ、あなたは読むのが速い。
"Wow, you read fast."
Ben can't hike very far.
Ben... can't... hike? Hike. Very far.
ベンはハイキングで遠くまで行けない。
Ben can't go very far hiking.
I eat lots of fruit.
たくさんの…
A lot of...
たくさん果物を食べます。
I eat a lot of fruit.
のじゃ！のじゃ！
Noja! Noja!
I don't eat lots of fruit.
のぉ...
No...
I can't surf very well.
I... can't... surf... very... well.
上手にサーフィンできないのじゃ。うん。
I can't surf very well, noja. Yeah.
Here is the towel, catch!
タオルだよ、タオルだよ...
Here is the towel, here is the towel...
...キャッチして。
...catch it!
うん。
Yeah.
Yes, your friend can join us.
Yes, your... friend... can... join... us.
あんたの友達も来ていいよ。うん。
Your friend can join us too. Yeah.
That player always catches the ball.
あのプレイヤーはいつもキャッチします。
When can we play the next game?
When... can... we play...
...the... next... game?
いつになったら次の試合を遊べますか？のじゃ。オッケー。
When can we play the next game, noja? Okay.
Can Lisa surf well?
上手にできましたか？オッケー。
Did she do it well? Okay.
The dog never catches the ball.
それはそうなのじゃ。犬はできない。
That is so true. Dogs can't do that.
Dog can't. But Salamander can. Yes.
Dogs can't, but salamanders can! Yes.
どこで空手ができますか？あ、Where...
Where can they do karate? Ah, where...
Where... 疑問！はてな！Question!
Where... Question! Question mark!
can... Where... can... they... do... karate.
Yes. Where... question can, and... subject, they do karate.
Yes. "Where", question "can", and the subject, "they do karate".
オッケー。オッケー。Great.
Okay. Okay. Great.
のじゃーー！
Noja!
できたのじゃーー！
I did it!
クリアのじゃーー！
Clear, noja!
オッケー。Today's...
Okay. Today's...
Duolingo complete noja. お部屋に戻るのじゃ。
Duolingo is complete, noja! Going back to my room.
よいしょ。うん。
Heave-ho. Yeah.
のじゃEnglish... complete noja today's noja English. Yes.
Noja English is complete for today, noja! Yes.
Good. Great. Did you have fun? Yes, really fun!
あ、except for the... あと、野菜食べろ、vegetable、eat vegetables、eat healthy foodは...
Ah, except for the... you know, "eat vegetables", "eat healthy food"...
...not fun, but... あの、それ以外はね、うん、fun. Yes.
...those weren't fun. But other than that, yeah, it was fun! Yes.
Great work noja. Yes.
うん、not eat veggies. No no no no.
Yeah, no eating veggies. No, no, no, no.
I, I, I don't like, I don't like... I, I like pancakes. I don't like veggies. No veggies.
I don't like veggies. I like pancakes! No veggies.
No fruits, no veggies. Only meat.
Give all sugary snacks to Mela. Yes, please! Please, sugary fruits, please.
うん、Yes.
Yeah, yes.
Veggies on pancake? No! No no no no no! パンケーキはパンケーキ。クレープ好きのじゃ。クレープ好きのじゃ。
"Veggies on a pancake?!" No! No, no, no, no! Pancakes are pancakes. I like crepes. I like crepes!
Yes, I like crepes.
のじゃ。あ、で、前回「言う」って言って言ってなかったから言ってあげよう。
Noja. Oh, right, I didn't say it last time, so let me tell you now.
Where I learn... learn English? どこでわし、英語学んだと思う？You guys.
Where did I learn English? Where do you think I learned English? From you guys!
どこでわしは英語を学んだと思いますか？のじゃ。
Where do you think I learned English, noja?
うん、なんか、あの次、次教えてあげるって言ってた。「山」。山？Mountain? Mountain? 「ママとパパ？」
Yeah, I said I'd tell you next time. "Mountain"? Mountain? Mountain? "Mom and Dad?"
「留学してた？」留学してない。留学？洋画？
"Did you study abroad?" I didn't study abroad. Studying abroad? Foreign movies?
「今日は、あの、映画で学んだって言ってたよね」。School? 「掲示板？」掲示板？Redditとか見てた？YouTube？
"You said today that you learned from movies, right?" School? "Message boards?" Message boards? Like, looking at Reddit? YouTube?
英会話教室？
"English school?"
海外行ったことある？
"Have I been overseas?"
Japanese yama... Japanese mountain.
Oh, yes.
Internet?
サラマンダーに友達がいた？サラマンダー、一人、サラマン。
"Did the salamander have friends? I was a lone salamander."
うーん
"Hmm..."
のじゃのじゃのじゃ
"Noja, noja, noja."
ENの先輩？
"My EN senpais?"
留学してる感じない？日本の英語教育？
"It doesn't feel like I studied abroad? Japanese English education?"
アニメ？
"Anime?"
ボーカロイド？
"Vocaloid?"
帰国子女？山？アニメ？
"Returnee? Mountain? Anime?"
英語教室？
"English school?"
じゃあ答え！答えは！
"So, the answer! The answer is..."
えっと、わしはちっちゃい、ちっちゃい？
"Well, when I was a little..."
人間、低学年の頃
"human in lower elementary school,"
えっとね、えっとね
"well, well..."
海外に住んでたのじゃ！
"I was living overseas!"
Yes.
帰国子女 is correct!
"Returnee is correct!"
うーん
"Hmm."
人間、低学年の頃ののじゃ。
"It was when I was in lower elementary."
山から下りて
"I came down from the mountain,"
父と母に拾われて
"was picked up by my mother and father,"
そう、ちょっとした時に、あの
"and after a little while,"
海外に住んでた。
"I lived overseas."
うーん
"Yeah."
から発音だけが良い。
"So, only my pronunciation is good."
発音だけが良いけど、あの
"Only my pronunciation is good, but..."
のじゃ？
"Noja?"
その文法とかはわからないのじゃ。
"I don't really know grammar and stuff."
うーん
"Yeah."
一年しかいなかったけど。
"Though I was only there for a year."
Yes, only one year!
そう、one year
"Yes, one year"
住んでて
"I lived there,"
そこで英語覚えた。
"and that's where I learned English."
うーん
"Yeah."
Yes, Mela grew up overseas?
いや、not grew up だけど、あの、one yearに
"No, not grew up, but I was there"
いた。
"for one year."
うーん
"Yeah."
のじゃ
"Noja."
一年で英検2級？
"Pre-2nd grade Eiken in one year?"
現地校に行ってたから、
"Because I went to a local school,"
そう、一年で発音うまくなった。
"yeah, my pronunciation got good in one year."
Yes, I lived overseas for one year. Yes.
So, I remember the
pronunciation, but
not the grammar. Yes.
うーん
"Yeah."
のじゃ
"Noja."
Yes.
Study stay? Not study stay, あの、ファミリーで
"Study abroad? Not study abroad, but with my family,"
そう、my familyで
"yeah, with my family,"
そう、行ったのじゃ。
"I went there."
And I...
現地校... 現地校って何じゃ？ちょっと調べる。
"Local school... what is local school in English? Let me check."
えっと
"Um..."
今、翻訳アプリ見るのじゃ。
"I'm looking at a translation app."
えっと、I actually lived in... for a year
"Well, I actually lived in... for a year"
and went to a
local school.
Local school there.
Yes.
そう、local school。最初ね、
"Yes, a local school. At first,"
日本人学校行ってたんじゃけど、
"I went to a Japanese school,"
なんかあんま気に入らなくて、
"but I didn't really like it."
うん、気に入らなくて
"Yeah, I didn't like it,"
現地校に引っ越した、転校した。
"so I transferred to a local school."
Did you make friends? Yes! 友達できたのじゃ！
"Did you make friends? Yes! I made friends!"
友達できた！
"I made friends!"
なんか、あの、
"And also,"
友達がね、あの、日本語で手紙とか書いてくれたよ。
"my friends wrote me letters in Japanese."
Japanese letter くれた。
"They gave me a Japanese letter."
Kind of friend いっぱいいたのじゃ。
"I had a lot of kind friends."
Yes.
Hola, can you Spanish? あの、なんか
"Hola, can you Spanish? Well, kinda..."
あの、
"Well..."
Spanishね、なんか
"Spanish, like..."
local school行ってた時にね、スペイン語の授業あったのじゃ。
"When I was at the local school, we had Spanish classes."
Yes, hola.
から、あの、holaだけわかる。
"So, I only know 'hola'."
Yes.
I know only hola.
Little, yes.
Were there Japanese teachers? No!
Japanese teacherも、
"No Japanese teachers,"
Japanese studentもいなかった。
"and no Japanese students either."
No.
誰も。
"Nobody."
Only me.
わしだけ。
"Just me."
わしだけJapanese.
"I was the only Japanese."
のじゃ。
Noja.
Yes.
それほぼほにゃららに住んでたって言っているようなもんだわ。
That's basically like saying you lived in...
あんま隠してないのじゃ。
I'm not really hiding it, noja.
あんま隠してないけど、あの、明言はしていないのじゃ。
I'm not really hiding it, but I haven't explicitly stated it, noja.
Yes, noja.
サラマンダーわししかいなかったのじゃ。
I was the only salamander there, noja.
Yes.
のじゃ、のじゃ。
Noja, noja.
Yes.
So, I can speak English, little bit.
そういうことだったのじゃ。
That's how it was, noja.
種明かし。種明かしのじゃ。
The reveal. The reveal, noja.
Yes.
うん。
Yeah.
Yes.
で、あの、日本に帰ったあととかも
And, even after returning to Japan...
その、勉強、イングリッシュの授業とかはあった、イングリッシュクラスみたいなのはあって
I had English classes, like, there were English classes...
あの、勉強はしたんじゃが、テストとかも感覚でやってしまって
And I did study, but I would take tests based on intuition.
そう、感覚でやってしまって、気づいたら分からなくなっていた、みたいな。
Relying on intuition, and before I knew it, I stopped understanding it.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなっていた。
Before I knew it, it became super difficult.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなって
Before I knew it, it got really hard...
あの、つまずいて、ボロボロじゃった。
And I stumbled and did terribly.
うん、たぶん帰国子女あるあるだと思うんじゃが、
Yeah, I think it's a common thing for returnees, but...
あの、中学、高校受験まではいけたんじゃが、
I managed up through junior high and high school entrance exams,
高校入って、文法とかもボロボロで分からなくなっちゃって、
but once I entered high school, my grammar was a mess and I didn't understand it anymore.
あの、気づいたらもう誰よりも英語わからないみたいになって、
Before I knew it, I was worse at English than anyone else.
そう、今も、今こんな。
Yeah, and now, here I am like this.
から、えーっと、
So, um...
デュオリンゴでね、
With Duolingo,
デュオリンゴで、えーっと、グラマー、グラマーを勉強する、yes。
with Duolingo, um, studying grammar, grammar, yes.
Study grammar, and
英語をもっと上手になりたい。
I want to get better at English.
Yes.
"I feel like you underestimate yourself." 本当？
"I feel like you underestimate yourself." Really?
"I'd say your English ability is better than just 'I know a bit.'" 本当？ Really?
"I'd say your English ability is better than just 'I know a bit.'" Really? Really?
やった、thank you, noja.
Yay, thank you, noja.
Yes, vocabulary and grammar
を練習したい、と思っていますのじゃ。
is what I want to practice, that's what I'm thinking, noja.
本当？「めっちゃ上手。英語上手」めっちゃ言われる。
Really? "You're so good. Your English is great," people say that a lot.
やったのじゃ！Thank you, noja!
Yay, noja! Thank you, noja!
Yes.
来週も、next weekも
Next week as well, next week too,
Wednesday, Wednesday,
on Wednesday, Wednesday,
AM 7:00
at 7:00 AM,
Japanese Standard Time
に、English, Englishをします！
I will do English, English!
Yes, します！
Yes, I will!
See you next Wednesday. Yes, okay.
In English, usually 7:00 AM. 7 AM.
うん。
Yeah.
Study ちりつもなのじゃ。
Study is step by step, noja.
コツコツ勉強して上手になって、
Studying little by little and getting better,
you guysとonly English streamが出来るようになるまで
until I can do an only English stream with you guys,
頑張りたいのじゃ！
I want to do my best, noja!
Yes.
Okay. So Tuesday evening for English speakers. Yes, yes, そうなのじゃ。
Okay. So Tuesday evening for English speakers. Yes, yes, indeed, noja.
頑張るのじゃ！
I'll do my best, noja!
"With Kyoko sometime?" Yes.
やりたい。キョウコとEnglish streamいずれやりたいのじゃ。
I want to do it. I'd love to do an English stream with Kyoko eventually, noja.
Yes, "vegetables", "no vegetables". "No vegetables".
Yes.
Okay then, see you next Wednesday, noja.
最後の挨拶は
My final greeting...
さらばじゃ。さらばじゃでおしまいにしますのじゃ。
is "saraba ja." Let's end with "saraba ja," noja.
それじゃ、everyone see you next Wednesday, noja!
Well then, everyone see you next Wednesday, noja!
さらばじゃ！
Saraba ja!
ご視聴感謝なのじゃ！
Thank you for watching!